<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Minucius Felix his dialogne [sic] called Octavius Containing a defence of Christian religion. Translated by Richard Iames of C.C.C. Oxon.</title>
            <title>Octavius. English</title>
            <author>Minucius Felix, Marcus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112688</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847934</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07567)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 674:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Minucius Felix his dialogne [sic] called Octavius Containing a defence of Christian religion. Translated by Richard Iames of C.C.C. Oxon.</title>
                  <title>Octavius. English</title>
                  <author>Minucius Felix, Marcus.</author>
                  <author>James, Richard, 1592-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 165, [19] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, for Thomas Huggins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: M. Minucius Felix his Octavius.</note>
                  <note>With six final leaves of verse; the three last leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17953a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MINVCIVS FELIX His dialogue called <hi>OCTAVIVS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing a defence of Chriſtian religion.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated by RICHARD IAMES of C. C. C. <hi>OXON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD, <hi>for Thomas Huggins.</hi> 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO MY LADY COTTON,</hi> Wife vnto <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROBERT COTTON</hi> of Conington.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME I haue receiued many favours from you, and doe in thankfullneſſe preſent
<pb facs="tcp:13003:3"/>
vnto your Ladiſhippe this my tranſlation of <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogue which conſiſts of three ſpeakers, <hi>M. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nucius Felix, Cecilius Natalis,</hi> and <hi>Octavius Ianuarius.</hi> The one is judge, the other produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a flouriſhing ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all the arguments of the Gentiles againſt Christian religion, and the third makes vnto them ſuch cleare an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare
<pb facs="tcp:13003:3"/>
as I belieue it will reioyce a Chriſtian reader to vnderſtand. Wherefore as the better ſort of Greekes, Romans, Italian, French and others haue taken a pleaſure to render vnto their owne nation what they found worthy in other languages, I in this litle peece haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed their example, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necting vnto it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of my owne, for
<pb facs="tcp:13003:4"/>
neareneſſe of ſubject, pray Madame let either haue your acceptance, and know me</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull ſervant RICHARD IAMES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>WHoſoeuer peruſeth this litle booke or any other of aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times, it behooues him to vſe ſobriety in his vnderſtanding, leaſt hee miſcarry either in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or diſcipline. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Minutius</hi> ſaith, the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Chriſtians had no Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: you muſt not therefore collect, that wee ought to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God only in fields or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate houſes. They had not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, <hi>Delubra,</hi> Temples of Jdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry: wherein the Gentiles vſed as <hi>Prudentius</hi> hath it <hi>deaſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ato ſupplicare ſtipiti to</hi> make their orizons to a peece of hewd timber, yet as it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant out of all antiquitie, they had according to the ſufferance
<pb facs="tcp:13003:5"/>
of times, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> houſes built to the honour of our Lord and Saviour, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Churches: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, houſes of prayer, oratories: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtately piles of buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in which they did meete to ſolemnize the dutyes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, and to heare the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious inſtructions of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates: More for the preſent I haue not to ſay. Let all things be done decently and in good order. This is a neceſſary remembrance from the Apoſtle, and ſo I wiſh the health of body and minde.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:5"/>
            <head>M. MINVCIVS <hi>FELIX HIS</hi> OCTAVIVS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mind the memorie of my good &amp; moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full companion <hi>Octavius,</hi> I was poſſeſt with ſo great a ſweetneſſe and affection of the man, that I euen ſeemed to returne vnto times paſt, and not only to recollect our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13003:6"/>
by way of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance; the contemplation of him being not ſo much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen from my eyes, as it is enfolded in my breaſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſenſes. And certainly the worth of that excellent holy man was ſuch, as it muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity leaue with me an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite deſire of him. He had a flagrancie of loue towards me, our wits bore conſort as well for recreation as buſineſſe, and we ever will'd and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſame things. You would haue thought us one ſoule divided into two bodies. He was alone private of my loues, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of my errors; and when, the miſt breaking out of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found darkneſſe, I did riſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the light of wiſdome, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13003:6"/>
truth, ſo farre he was from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking my ſocietie, as to his greater glory, he did runne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to direct me the way. And when my thoughts had runne over all the age of our familiar acquaintance, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of my minde did more eſpecially abide vpon that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of his, by which, in a moſt graue diſputation, he did reforme vnto true religion <hi>Cecilius</hi> then adhering to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious vanities. For cauſe of buſineſſe, and to ſee me, he had taken a iourney to Rome, leauing his houſe, wife and children, and that which is in children moſt louely, their yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnocent yeares, when they ſtriue at halfe wordes, in a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage more pleaſing, by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13003:7"/>
pretty breach of their tripping tongues. I cannot with words expreſſe vnto you, how this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivall of his did rauiſh me into an exceſſe of gladneſſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the vnexſpected preſence of a moſt deare friend: Then after a day or two, when fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent vſance had taken off the impatience of our deſire, when wee had learned from mutuall relation what wee knew not of each other in time of abſence, we did agree to view <hi>Oſtia,</hi> a moſt pleaſant Cittie, becauſe for drying vp the humours of my body a faire and appoſite cure it is, to walke by the waues of the Sea. It was vacation from all judiciall cares, by reaſon of the Vintage; and the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13003:7"/>
of Autumne, did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what temper the aire from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival heat. So then vpon break of day, when we went forth to pace vpon the ſhoare, the aire gently breathing vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to our members, and the ſoft ſand with a fine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſomewhat yeelded to the impreſſion of our feet, <hi>Cecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſpying the image of <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis,</hi> as ſuperſtitious people are wont to doe, lifting his hands vnto his mouth, made them kiſſe his lips. Then ſpake <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius.</hi> Tis not the part of a good man, brother <hi>Marke,</hi> ſo to neglect him who is alwaies both at home and abroad euer by your ſide; as that you ſhould ſuffer him through vulgar blindneſſe, in cleare day to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13003:8"/>
ſtumble at ſtones, howſoeuer they bee ſhaped into image, ſmoothed with oile, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with flowers; when you know that the infamie of ſuch errour, doth no leſſe fall on you then him. And with ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of his, hauing paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver halfe the ſpace of the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we had now gotten vpon the open ſhoare, where the gentle waue, as if it tooke plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſtrow vs a faire walke, did levell the outward ſands: The Sea when the winds are all laid, is neuertheleſſe reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in it ſelfe, and although it came not on, with white foaming billowes, yet had they a curl'd wallowing courſe. There wandering vp and downe, wee did much ſolace
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13003:8"/>
our ſelues, and did endanger the ouerflowing of our feete, in the brinck of the Sea, which would play vp her waues, and againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lyding back, receiue them into her owne boſome. So in a ſtealing quiet pace ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king forward, we forgot our way with diſcourſe, along the eaſie bending of the ſhoare; and this diſcourſe was, a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Octavius,</hi> opening the courſe of navigation. But when we had thus talked out a ſufficient journie, turning our ſteps, wee did againe pace ouer the ſame way. And when we came vnto the place where little boates drawne vp from the water lay on rowlers, to preſerue them from occaſion of rotting, wee ſaw Children
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13003:9"/>
ſportfully contending who ſhould skeere ſhells fartheſt vpon the top of the Sea. The ſport is to gather vp from the ſhoare a round ſhell, ſmoothen. with the beating of the wanes, and taking of it flat in their fingers to make long circling ejaculations vpon the water, the ſhell razing, gliding, or leaping there, ſo long as it hath force of motion; and that child beares the victorie whoſe ſhell doth glide fartheſt, or leape more often. When therefore all of vs were taken with the pleaſure of this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, <hi>Cecilius</hi> only intended nothing, neither would hee laugh to ſee this contention of the children, but by ſilence anxietie and by-walking, alſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13003:9"/>
in his very viſage hee ſeem'd afflicted with ſomething which wee knew not. Then quoth I, what is this matter? why doe we not find in <hi>Ceci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> his wonted alacritie? why doe we not ſee that cheerefull countenance which hee vſeth to preſerue in times of greater reſidue? Then hee replied, I haue indeed beene a good while bitterly vexed, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with our <hi>Octavius</hi> his words, when invectiuely hee reproued you of negligence, that he might more cunningly put on me the greater ſcorne of ignorance. Therefore I will goe farther. I haue to doe with <hi>Octavius</hi> vpon the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, if he be willing to diſpute it with me, who am a man of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13003:10"/>
that ſect which hee ſo much vnder values. Surely he will quickly know how farre more eaſie it is to prate amongſt Goſſips, then to trie his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with a man of an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite vnderſtanding. Then on this terrace of rocks, made to defend the incurſion of the ſea from the bathes, let vs ſit downe, that we may both reſt from our journey, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter intend our diſputation. He had no ſooner ſpoken the word, but we ſate downe. I in the middeſt, ambitiouſly protected with them on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, not by way of obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiouſneſſe, order, or honour, (ſince freindſhip doth finde or make equality amongſt men) but as an Vmpire, the better
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13003:10"/>
to heare both, and to keepe two earneſt diſputants aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Then <hi>Cecilius</hi> thus began. Although brother <hi>Marcus</hi> thoſe things of which we ſhall make enquirie, ſeeme not to you ambiguous, who having beene diligently converſant in both kinds of life, haue refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the one, and approued the other, neuertheleſſe for the preſent, you are ſo to order your minde, that you like an equall iudge, hold the skales, propenſive unto neither ſide, leaſt the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence you ſhal paſſe, rather proceede from your owne apprehenſion then the force of our arguments. Wherefore if you ſit here as a ſtranger, and ignorant of either partie, it will be no buſineſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13003:11"/>
to ſhew, that all thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men are doubtfull, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, pendulous, and rather probable then true, to the leſſe wonder of many, who wearie in the cleere ſearch of truth, rather quickly yeeld to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, then perſevere in a pertinacious diligence, to find it out. Wherefore with indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or pitie we ought to looke on ſome; who vnſtudied, illiterate, vncunning in all arts but ſordid, dare peremptorily decree maximes of Divine Maieſtie, wherein Philoſophie it ſelfe, through ſo many ages and variety of ſects can but yet deliberate: And not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe; ſince humane me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity, is ſo farre from reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Divine things, as thoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13003:11"/>
things which are aboue vs in heauen ſuſpended and ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, or hid in the profundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the earth beneath vs, no abilitie haue we to know, tis not permitted to ſearch, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther religious to queſtion. And enough happy, and enough prudent, we may deſervedly be accounted, if according to the old Oracle of wiſedome, we be familiar in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſelues. But ſince ouer indulgent to a madde vaine curioſitie, we will needs wander beyond the limits of our meane condition, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend with a bold deſire euen heaven and the ſtarres them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, let vs ſee whether we may a little ſtay this error with an earneſt and vndaunted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13003:12"/>
diſquiſition. If the ſeeds of the elements doe naturally come together, and condenſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> themſelues, why muſt God be here an author? If by caſuall concurſion, the members of the vniuerſe doe ioyne, are dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and formed, why muſt Divinitie contriue the worke? If fire kindle the ſtarres, and the celeſtiall matter ſublime it ſelfe, if the earth haue foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in his owne weight, and the ſea flow out of moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, why is this religion, this feare, this ſuperſtition? Man and every creature that is borne, hath his being from breath and nouriſhment; this is the voluntary concretion of the elements into which man and every creature elſe is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13003:12"/>
diſſolued, and ſcattered. So all things returne into the fountaine of themſelues, with a naturall revolution, without artificer, judge, or author. So we euery day ſee new Sunnes, from the elementarie ſeeds of fire collected together, new cloudes, growing from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haled vapours of the earth; theſe riſe, thicken, and coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in the aire, then with their owne weight fall downe into flux of raine, blaſt of wind, and ſtorme of haile, or in colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion make rowling claps of thunder, flaſhes of lightning; and if boults fly out, they fall any where, ruſh on moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, beare downe trees, touch Temples no leſſe then profane houſes, ſtrike impious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13003:13"/>
men, and often the moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. What ſhall I ſpeake of tempeſts alike various and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, without order, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examination, hurling im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuouſly where they light. In ſhipwrack alike deſtiny mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the good with the bad, and confounds their merits; fire diſcernes not the innocent from the guiltie, and when any tract of heauen is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with peſtilent contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all die without difference. When the furie of warre ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, the beſt people fall ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, alſo in peace many times wickedneſſe is not only equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd but exalted aboue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and in many wicked, a man knowes not whether he ſhould more hate their impietie, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13003:13"/>
bleſſe their fortune. But if the world were govern'd by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, neuer ſhould <hi>Phalaris</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> merit a kingdome, <hi>Rutilius</hi> and <hi>Camilius</hi> bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with baniſhment, and <hi>Socrates</hi> with poyſon. Behold the trees laden with fruite, the fieldes white unto the harveſt, theſe and the full-growne vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage are corrupted with ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or beaten downe with haile. So is truth either hidden and kept to vs vncertaine, or, that which is moſt credible from theſe divers lubricities of chance, fortune free from all lawes doth ſeignorize the world. When therefore either fortune is certaine, or nature vncertaine, how much better
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13003:14"/>
is it, and more venerable, to receiue the diſcipline of our Aunceſtors for tradition of truth, obſerue the religions left vs by them, to adore thoſe Gods, which thy Parents haue from thy youth familiarly taught thee to feare and know, then to ſit in judgment vpon the Gods. Let vs beleeue our firſt Parents, who ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the ſimple infancie of the world, did deſerue to haue the Gods, or their Princes more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vnto them. And by this meanes through all Empires, Provinces, Citties, we ſee them haue their ſeverall nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall ſacred rites, and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their municipall Gods the <hi>Eleuſinians C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> the <hi>Phrygians,</hi> the great Mother,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13003:14"/>
the <hi>Epidaurians Aeſculapius,</hi> the <hi>Chaldeans Belus,</hi> the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians Aſtarte,</hi> the <hi>Tauricians Diana,</hi> the <hi>Gaules Mercurie,</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> all. So hath their power and authoritie ſubdued the circumference of the whole world, propagated their Empire beyond the courſe of the Sunne, and limits of the Ocean; Whileſt with their armes they exerciſe a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vertue; whileſt they forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the cittie with ſacred re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, chaſt Virgins, many honours and titles of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: whileſt beſeiged, and all taken but the Capitoll, they ſtil worſhip thoſe Gods, which ſome would in anger haue diſpiſed, &amp; through the troups of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> wondering at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13003:15"/>
their bold ſuperſtition, they paſſe naked of weapons, but armed with a worſhip of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: whileſt now captiue in their owne hoſtile walls, and victory purſuing execution on them, they ſtill reverence their conquer'd Deities; whil'ſt from euery quarter they ſeeke forraine Gods, and make them their owne: whileſt they ſet vp altars to vnknowne Gods, and ſpirits, and doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the ſacred ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of all nations, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued their Empire. This perpetuall courſe of religion hath hitherto remained, not broken with antiquitie but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. For age vſeth to giue to ceremonies and temples ſo much more ſanctity, as they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13003:15"/>
haue augmentation of yeares. Neither yet, (for I dare here yeeld to make the ſearch, and ſo erre with more authority) did our anceſtors in ſearching entralls, ordaining rites, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating temples, raſhly ſpend their labour. View the memory of bookes, and you ſhall quickly finde, that they did initiate themſelues into the rites of all religions, either to gratifie divine favour, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert imminent anger of the Gods, or to aſſwage it being in full rage, and fury. Witneſſe the <hi>Jdean</hi> mother, which at her arrivall approu'd the chaſtity of a Matrone, and did free the citty from hoſtile feare. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the conſecrate ſtatues of <hi>Caſtor,</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> as they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13003:16"/>
ſhewed themſelues in the lake, their horſes all in a heate panting and foming, when they reported our victory ouer <hi>Perſes,</hi> the ſame day he was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome. Witneſſe the itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great playes in the <hi>Circus,</hi> to reconcile the offence of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> according to the dreame of a vulgar Citizen. Witnes the ratified devotion of the <hi>Docians;</hi> and witneſſe <hi>Curtius,</hi> who with leaping himſelfe downe on horſeback, into the ſwallow of a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious deepe gulfe, made it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine fill vp. And more often then wee would, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of augurie, haue made manifeſt the preſence of the Gods. Thence is the name of <hi>Allia</hi> diſmall, thence did <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13003:16"/>
and <hi>Iunins,</hi> in their ſea-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight with the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> ſuffer a cruell ſhipwrack. And to make the river <hi>Thraſymene</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un high and diſcoloured with our blood, <hi>Flaminius</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned the prediction of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irdes: and to make vs new worke for the recovering our Enſignes from the <hi>Parthians, Craſſus</hi> did ſcorne, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the Prieſts holy impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions. I omitte many antique memories, of the birthes, gifts, and munificence of the Gods, I neglect the Poets ſongs, I paſſe ouer many deſtinies fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by Oracles, leaſt antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie may ſeeme vnto you ouer-fabulous. Behold the Temples, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſtatuary houſes of the Gods, with which the Cittie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13003:17"/>
of Rome is protected, and beautified: they are more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and rich in dreſſing and gifts, then venerable with thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Deities, dwelling, abiding, and euer ready for preſent helpe in them. From thence Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets full of God, and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating the divine nature, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther predictions of things to come, forewarne evile, giue cures for diſeaſes, hope to the afflicted, ſolace in calamities caſe in labours: alſo in our ſteep there, we ſee the Gods, wee heare them, we acknowledge their preſence: how ſoon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the day we denie, violate thee honours, and forſweare b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them. Therefore when in all nations there remaines a firme confeſſion of the immortal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13003:17"/>
Gods, although their cauſe and originall be vncertaine, I can brooke no man, who puft vp with I knowe not what bold irreligious wiſedome, dare attempt to diſſolue and elevate this religion of ours ſo old, ſo vſefull, ſo preſerving humane ſocietie. Away with <hi>Theodore</hi> of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> and with <hi>Diagoras Melius</hi> before him, vpon whom antiquitie puts the name of <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> both which in their doctrine of no Gods, tooke away all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent feare and awfulneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y which mankind is gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Theſe men in their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of impietie, although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey diſſemble Philoſophie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall neuer be reputed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. When the <hi>Athenians</hi> did
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13003:18"/>
baniſh out of their territories, <hi>Protagoras</hi> of <hi>Abdera,</hi> who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted rather indiſcreetly then prophanely of Divinitie, &amp; did in their aſſembly burne his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; (you will ſuffer me to proſecute my vndertaken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with a free zeale) muſt not we mourne to behold men, men I ſay of an incurable, ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and deſperate faction, ſo to forrage vpon the Gods? who with a collection of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple drawen from vtter baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and with credulous woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eaſily falling in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillitie of their ſexe, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute a route and profane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, which in their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturnall congregations, by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne faſts, and inhumane feaſts, things not of Sacramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13003:18"/>
but expiation doe league to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, a lurking and light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyding nation, full of prate in Corners, and dumbe in faire aſſemblies. They diſpiſe our Temples as graues, they ſpit vpon the Gods, and deride our ſacred Ceremonies. If a man may ſpeake it, theſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable creatures with pittie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the honours of our Prieſts, and halfe naked ſcorne our Purple. O their wonderfull and incredible bold foolerie. In feare of vncertaine future torments they diſpiſe all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and here they feare not to die, for feare of dying after death. So doth feare and falſe hope flatter them into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of living againe. And now as euill things grow in greateſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13003:19"/>
abundance, pernicious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners creeping in, theſe men haue gained every where in the worlde terrible aſſemblies of their impious combination, a combination accurſed and to bee plucked vp by the very rootes. They know themſelues by ſecret markes and tokens, they are in loue almoſt before they know one another, and promiſcuous luſt is with them a kind of religion, for they are all brothers and ſiſters, ſo that by interceſſion of ſo holy a name, common fornication muſt of neceſſity be with them inceſt. So doth this vaine mad ſuperſtition glory in being cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall. Neither would wiſe diſcerning common fame, (if there were no ſubſiſtencie of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13003:19"/>
truth) report theſe horrid things of them, things not to be vttered without a preface of honour to the hearers. I heare that amongſt all filthy beaſts, from what perſwaſion I know not, they worſhip an Aſſes head, like worſhip like manners. Others report that they worſhip their Prelates and Prieſts privie members, adoring the nature of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Parents. Peradventure this ſuſpition may bee falſe, yet it well agrees with a ſecret nocturnall ſolemnitie. But thoſe which ſay their worſhip to bee a man put to death for criminall demerit, and that they worſhip the horrid ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes of his croſſe, theſe fit thoſe wicked loſt people with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13003:20"/>
alters in a good congruitie, making them adore that which they deſerue. Now of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving new commers into their ſect, the report is not ſo deteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table as notorious. An Infant is covered ouer in meale to deceiue the Novice, and ſet before him, then is he provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as it were with harmeleſſe ſtrokes to ſtab into the meale, and ſo by concealed woundes the Infant is kil'd. O horrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe! this Infants blood they lick vp, and divide his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers amongſt them; with this ſacrifice they are imbrued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a league, and by the guilt of murder giue pledge vnto mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſecrecie. If this be ſacred, what is ſacrilegious? And the manner of their feaſting is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13003:20"/>
well knowne, all men every where report it, and it is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in the Oration of our <hi>Certenſian Fronto,</hi> vpon a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne day they come together to feaſt, with all their children, ſiſters, mothers, people of all ſexes, and all ages. There after much gluttonie, when the banquet is warme, and the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vencie of inceſtuous luſt is ſet on fire with wine, a dogge tied to the candleſtick, is by ſcraps caſt beyond the length of the line wherewith he is bound, provoked to leap impetuouſly forth, &amp; then the diſcovering light being ouerturn'd and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, each takes his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in the impudent darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherewith to ſatiate their abhominable appetite,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13003:21"/>
and ſo are they all if not in deed, yet inconſcience alike inceſtuous, all deſiring that which is by any acted. Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly I paſſe by many things, ſince what already is related is more then ſhould bee, true in all, or the greateſt part, as a man will eaſily belieue from the obſcuritie of this impious religion. For why ſhould they otherwiſe ſtriue with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to hide and keepe ſecret that whatſoeuer it be which they worſhip. Sinnes reſerue themſelues, and things honeſt reioyce in the publique view of men. Why haue they no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, no temples, no knowen images of their worſhip? Why dare they not ſpeake openly, and make their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13003:21"/>
freely, except that which they worſhip and conceale ſo narrowly were either a matter of puniſhment or ſhame. Or from whence, who, or where is he, their onely ſolitarie and deſtitute Deitie, whom no free nation, no Empires, no <hi>Roman</hi> ſuperſtition euer heard of? The miſerable tribes of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> they indeed, and they alone worſhip one God, but they doe it openly with temples, altars, ſacrifices, ceremonies; whoſe vigour notwithſtanding and power is ſo nothing, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Gods haue taken him captiue with all his nation. And what monſters, what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies doe the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s faine? That God whom they can neither ſhew nor ſee, they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13003:22"/>
make inquiſitiue into all the manners of men, all the deeds, yea even into the very words and ſecret thoughts of all, poſting every where, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where preſent. They will haue him troubleſome, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and impudently curious, ſtanding by at all actes, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errant in all places, when no ſufficiency ſtraind with a vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall care can intend the ſervice of every particular, nor diſtracted with particulars can ſuffice for an vniverſall preſeruation. Why, and to the whole earth, even to the Heavens alſo and the Starres they threaten a combuſtion, and prepare a ruine, as if the eternall order of nature ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Divine lawes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13003:22"/>
might ever bee troubled, or the league of all the Elements broken, and the heavenly frame divided, all this all in whoſe continent and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing circle wee haue our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhould bee ſubverted. Nor contented with this fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious opinion they hang and knit vnto it other olde wiues fables; how they ſhall bee borne anew after death, when they are aſhes and cinders; and I know not with what beliefe they aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their lyes; to heare all, you would thinke they were all ready in a reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A pernitious evill fanſie, and a double madneſſe! they denounce vtter confuſion to the Heavens and Starres,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13003:23"/>
which wee leaue as we finde, and to themſelues dead and extinct, for as wee are borne wee dye, they againe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe eternity. And for this reaſon they hold funerall fires in ſepulture a damnable execration; as if our bodies although ſaved from flames, ſhould not with yeares and ages bee diſſolued into earth; as if it were a thing materiall, whether the beaſts of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts did teare, or the fiſhes of the ſea conſume, or the earth cover, or the fire ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due our dead carcaſſes; when any ſepulture, if we did feele, were ſtill a puniſhment, and if wee feele nothing, then muſt a flaming buriall bee in her celerity the beſt cure of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13003:23"/>
rottenneſſe. So deceiued with this errour, to themſelues good men when they are dead they promiſe perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of life, and to others as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, ſempiternall torments. Much here might bee added; but I will haſten my diſcourſe, having allready ſufficiently declared that even they themſelues are the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous people. Nay if wee ſhould alſo grant them the title of righteouſneſſe, you or the greateſt part of you agree in ſentence, that innocencie of life or guiltineſſe ought to bee impoſed vpon a kinde of deſtiny. For whatſoeuer wee doe, as ſome addict the cauſe to deſtiny, you lay it vpon God, and vſe to ſay, that your
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13003:24"/>
ſect receiues not voluntarie but the elect? Wherefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you muſt needs haue an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iuſt Iudge, which doth puniſh in men not their will, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fortune. Yet I would fain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> learne of you, whether we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt come to this your reſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection without our bodye or with our bodyes, and wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what bodyes, the ſame, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with ſome innovation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them? If without the bodyes, for all that I know, out of a bodye, there is neither minde, nor ſoule, nor life: if with the bodye, is not that allready moultered away? With ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodye? Then is there a new man borne, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer not repaired: and yet in the fluxe and courſe of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13003:24"/>
hundred yeares and ages, what one with the earneſt fortune of <hi>Protesilaus</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from any infernall treaſuries of death, with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſome few houres new liuely-hood, that wee might belieue reſurrection by example. All theſe figments of braine-ſicke opinion, and theſe fooliſh comforts, ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out by deceitfull Poets in a ſweetneſſe of verſe, you in an over-credulity haue taken vp a new, and skervily impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them vpon your owne God. Neither will you learne experience from your owne preſent ſufferings: In them you might ſee with what vaine hope theſe promiſes feed their belieuers, and you
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13003:25"/>
might deeme by the miſery of your life what were more probable after death. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the greateſt part of you and the better as you ſay are cold and hungry, you haue no wealth, you pine with want and famine; and doth God ſuffer this, doth hee diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or will hee not, or can hee not helpe his good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Hee is then diſable, or vniuſt. Thou which doeſt dreame of an immortality af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou art layed in the graue, when with danger thou art ſhaken into a cold feare, when thou doeſt burne in a feaver, when thou art tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with paine, doeſt thou not then feele thine owne condition, doeſt thou not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13003:25"/>
thy fragility? Alas poore miſerable man, infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thus convincing thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy will, yet no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion! But theſe are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miſeries. See terrours vpon you, executions, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and now you muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe the Croſſe, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it, you muſt alſo bee burnt vp in fire, which you foretell and feare. Where is the God, who will helpe you to liue againe, can hee not ſaue you aliue? Doe not the <hi>Romanes</hi> without your God ſway their Empire, command and enioy the whole world, and domineere over you? You in the meane while penſiue and ſorrowfull, abſtaine from honeſt pleaſures, you come not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13003:26"/>
to any ſpectacles, are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at our pompes and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes, our publique feaſts are without your company, our meates and drinkes offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the Altars you abhorre, and all our ſacred ſportes, and ſo ſeeme to feare thoſe Gods you deny. You weaue no wreathes of flowres for your heads, you honour not your body with ſweete perfumes, but reſerue their vnction for funeralls, which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you refuſe to adorne with garlands; pale chivie people, and deſeruing pitty, but the pitty of our Gods. Miſerable men, you doe not yet riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to life, and in the meane while you liue not. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you haue in you any
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13003:26"/>
wiſdome or ſhame, leaue of ſearching the regions of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens with their fatalities and ſecrets. Tis enough for you to looke before your feete, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially being vnlearned, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliſht, rude and ruſticke. They to whome is not given power of vnderſtanding civill things, muſt of neceſſity bee farther diſable for diſquirie of things Divine. Alſo if any of you luſt after Philoſophy, the beſt of you may if he can, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate <hi>Socrates</hi> the very Prince of wiſdome, whoſe knowne anſweare it is when hee was at any time deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of celeſtiall matters, that which is aboue vs is to vs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and therefore worthily did hee from the Oracle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13003:27"/>
the teſtimony of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lar wiſdome, which he befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aprehended of himſelfe, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hee was therefore preferred before all others, not becauſe hee had comprehended al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things, but becauſe hee had learned that hee knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. So is chiefe wiſedome the confeſſion of our owne vnskilfullneſſe. And from this fountaine did flow the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ambiguity of <hi>Arceſilas, Carneades</hi> much after him, and of the greateſt ſort of the <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demickes</hi> in queſtions of high <hi>nature,</hi> and in this kind the vnlearned may ſafely, and the learned gloriouſly play the Philoſophers. The ſlowneſſe alſo of the <hi>Melian Simonides</hi> is it not admirable and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13003:27"/>
to bee followed? Who when hee was asked by the Tirant <hi>Hieron</hi> of what eſſence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd quality hee ſuppoſed the Gods to bee, required firſt a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay of deliberation, the next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay following gotte a proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of two dayes more, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine a like addition to that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd then when at laſt the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant enquired the cauſes of ſo great delay, made anſweare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he more time hee ſpent in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nquiſition, the more obſcure did this truth appeare vnto him. And in my opinion things doubtfull are to bee left as we finde them; neither in a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration of ſo many, and ſo great perſons, may wee without empeachment of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity and boldneſſe bring
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13003:28"/>
in our iudgement on either ſide, for feare leaſt we either deſtroy all religion, or induce for worſhip old wiues ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions. Thus ſpake <hi>Cecilius,</hi> &amp; then ſmiling, (for the fluxe of a long oration had allayed the tumour of his diſdaine) to theſe things ſaid hee, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply dares <hi>Octavius,</hi> a man of <hi>Plautus</hi> like progenie, of ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers the firſt, and the laſt of Philoſophers? I ſayd, forbeare to ſport on him, for you doe not worthily to triumph in concinnity of ſpeech, before hee hath fully ended his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration on the other ſide, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when your enquiry aymes not at praiſe but truth. And allthough your oration hath wonderfully delighted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13003:28"/>
me with the ſubtile variety of it, yet I conſider deepely not only for this action, but for the whole kinde and manner of diſputation, that many times, by the ability and power of the diſputants eloquence, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven things of cleare truth ſeeme to change their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This is well knowne to happen by the eaſineſſe of the hearers, who ſeduced with a delicacy of words are taken off from an intention of the things, aſſenting without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination to all that is ſpoken; not diſcerning falſe things from right, and vnwitting, that truth may bee in that which ſeemes incredible, and falſehood in the greateſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of truth. Therefore
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13003:29"/>
the more often they belieue earneſt aſſertions, more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are they againe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by skilfull men, and dayly beguild through their owne raſhneſſe, transferre the fault of iudgement into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of vncertainty, and at laſt condemning all things, had rather ſuſpect any thing, then put themſelues to the difficulty of iudging, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things bee falſe or no. Wherefore wee muſt haue a provident care leaſt with ſuch wee runne into a hatred of all enquiries, and at laſt breake forth as doe many of the more ſimple ſort, into an execration and hate of men alſo. For theſe vnheedfull credulous people when they are circumuented
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13003:29"/>
by thoſe whom they eſteemed good men, for feare of a like errour now ſuſpecting all things, diſtruſt thoſe as wicked alſo, whom otherwiſe they could approue for perſons of excellent goodneſſe. Since then in every matter there be who diſpute on both ſides, and truth is moſt often obſcure on the beſt, on the other lurkes wonderfull ſubtilty, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a copiouſneſſe of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence doth imitate the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of plaine evidence, it behooues vs to ponder all with diligence, ſo as we may giue ſubtile argumentation her due praiſe, yet make choice of thoſe things which are right, them onely approue and entertaine. You depart
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13003:30"/>
ſaith <hi>Cecilius,</hi> from the office of a faire iudge. For it is very iniurious for you to infringe the force of my action with interpoſing ſo graue a diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when <hi>Octavius</hi> is yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and vnblemiſht in what hee ſhall reply. If that, ſay I, which you haue in your decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation made ſo foule can bee refuted, then is this remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of mine brought in briefly for the common good of vs all, that wee may deliuer our iudgement from an exact examination, not ſwayed with blaſtes of eloquence, but with the ſolidity of the things themſelues. Neither will I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer ſtay our intention as you complaine, ſince if you pleaſe to giue a faire ſilence,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13003:30"/>
you may ſoone heare the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare of our <hi>Ianuarius,</hi> who ſeemes with ioye to prepare himſelfe. And then <hi>Octauius:</hi> I will, ſaith he, ſpeake accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my ability, and vſe all my ſtrength, yet muſt you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour with me to waſh of with a flood of true wordes his moſt bitter aſperſion of contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious reproches. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſſimulation firſt of all I muſt ſay, that my <hi>Natalis</hi> hath not deliuered his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with conſtancy, it hath erred, it hath flowen out, bin ready many times to ſlippe from it ſelfe. For hee varies ſometimes in a beliefe of the Gods, ſometimes in a delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, peraduenture to the end that by the vncertainty
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13003:31"/>
of his propoſition, the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our reply might with the leſſe certainty come home vnto him. But I will haue no craft in my <hi>Natalis,</hi> I doe not belieue it, cunning trade wit is farre from his ſimplicity. How then? As he that knowes not the right way, when hee comes where the way parts into divers turnings, he ſtands doubtfull, dares not chuſe any, nor approue all; ſo hee who hath no ſtable iudgement of truth, diſſipates and ſcatters his doubtfull minde with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of ſuſpitions. No mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle therefore if <hi>Cecilius</hi> bee alſo toſſed, tided, and waved vp and downe, in ſo many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant contrarieties. From which to ſet him ſafe I will
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13003:31"/>
convince and reproue all his diverſeneſſe with a diſcourſe that ſhall accept no proofe or confirmation but from truth only, hee ſhall no more doubt, no more wander. And becauſe my brother broke forth to ſay, how ill hee tooke it, how hee did ſtomack, diſdaine and grieue, that illiterate poore ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naroes ſhould diſpute of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall things, let him know that all men of what age ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſexe or dignity, are begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten capable, and able of reaſon and ſenſe, and haue not by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but nature an endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of wiſdome: and that Philoſophers themſelues or whoſoeuer by invention of arts hate attained famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, before by the ſolerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13003:32"/>
of their minde they got this glory, were in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance illiterate, halfe-naked Plebeians; that wealthy men even ſtaked vnto their riches, doe rather conſider gold then Heaven: and that theſe our poore men haue found out wiſdome, &amp; deliuered all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline to poſterity. Whence it appeareth, that wit is not an eſcheat of wealth, not compaſſed by ſtudy, but proceeding from the very information of the minde. Nor are we therefore to chafe or greiue, if any man whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he be, doe ſearch after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things, conceiue, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his ſentence: when not the authority of him that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, but ſtill the truth of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13003:32"/>
diſputation is to be required: and by how much the ſpeech is the more vnskilfull, ſo much more illuſtrious is the reaſon, not varniſht with a pompe and grace of eloquence, but ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as it ought to be, by the rule of right. Neither doe I refuſe that which <hi>Cecilius</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to obtaine, that a man ought to know himſelfe, and roundly conſider, what he is, whence he is, why he is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concrete of elements, compact of attomes, or rather made, faſhioned and animated by God; which we cannot try and make evident without an inquiſition of the whole vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; when things here are ſo coherent, knit and chained to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as if you doe not dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13003:33"/>
examine the reaſons of of divinity, we cannot kindly learne the condition of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature, neither may a man fairely handle civill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, except hee know the common city of the world in which all haue fellowſhip: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, becauſe from wilde and tame beaſtes we only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in this, that they groveling and turning to the earth, are borne to looke after nothing but their food; wee to whom an erect countenance, and an aſpect for the view of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is given, beſides ſpeech and reaſon, by which wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God, we feele &amp; reſemble him, muſt not here haue leaue of ignorance? when alſo a celeſtiall brightneſſe is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13003:33"/>
every where obvious to our eyes and ſenſes, and it ſeemes to me a crime no leſſe then the greateſt ſacrilege, to ſeeke on earth that which wee ought to finde in heaven. What minde, ſenſe, eyes can we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in them, who will haue the beauty of this world not perfected by divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but transformed into a globe by an infinity of pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces caſually tumbling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For what can bee ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, ſo credible, ſo cleare, when thou lifteſt thy eyes to heaven, and doſt conſider the glories of that high circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, as that there muſt needs be ſome Deity of moſt excellent ſpirit, by which all nature hath her inſpiration,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13003:34"/>
motion, nutrition, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? See heaven it ſelfe, how farre it is extended, how ſwiftly tis rowled about, ſee the night diaperd with ſtarres, ſee the day made illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious with the Sunne. Is not here a miraculous divine li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the great Maſter? Looke vpon the yeare how it is made by the Sunnes circling progreſſe, looke on the Moone how it wheeles about the month in an encreaſe, waine, and laſt quarter: what ſhall wee ſay to the interchanging viciſſitude of darkneſſe and light, to make vs an eternall reparation of worke and reſt? And to Aſtrologers we muſt leaue a more ample contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the ſtarres, how
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13003:34"/>
they governe the courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, or direct the ſeaſons of plowing and harveſt. All which things doe not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a perfect wiſdome and great artificer, for their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being, order, but alſo a mighty power of wit and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, to conceiue, diſcouer, and vnderſtand them. The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of times diſtinguiſhed with a conſtant variety of fruites, doth not this teſtify the authour and parent of it? The ſpring with his flowers, the ſummer with his harveſt, the welcome maturity of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne, and the oliue ſhaking winter are all of equall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. Which order would eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee confounded, if it did not conſiſt in greate wiſdome.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13003:35"/>
And it is alſo great provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that winter alone doth not burne with her froſt, or ſummer alone doth not ſcortch with heate, to inſert a midle temperament of autumne and ſpring; that the changes of the yeare returning in her owne trace, may ſlide about in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inoffenſiue revolution. Goe to the ſea, the law of the ſhoare bounds it. View all the trees that be, they haue their vegetation from the bowells of the earth, behold the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, there is reciprocall eſtua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her floods, ſee the fountaines, they ſpring from everlaſting veines, looke vnto the rivers, they glide along their wonted bankes. What ſhall I ſay of the ſteepe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13003:35"/>
the windeing hills, and the broad fields, how aptly they are diſpoſed. What ſhall I tell you the divers ſorts of defence which creatures haue one againſt another? ſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with hornes, other with teeth, vnderlayd with hoofes, and ear'd with ſharpe briſtles: or free in the ſwiftneſſe of feete, and flight of wings. But moſt of all doth the beauty of our ſhape ſhew God to bee the artificer, a ſtraight ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, an erect countenance, eyes placed aboue, as in a watch towre, and all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſes ranged as it were for the guarde of a caſtle. Tis long to goe through every part: there is no one member of a man which is not as well
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13003:36"/>
for cauſe of faireneſſe, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. And that which is more wonderfull, though we haue all the ſame figure, yet is there in ſingular perſons ſuch a deflexion of the lineaments, that wee appeare all alike, and all diſalike compared one with another. The condition of our birth, the deſire of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, is not this from the will of God, Who makes breſts in the maturation of the infant to fill with milke, with whoſe plenty the tender youngling may bee foſterd vp? Neither doth God only take care for the whole world, but alſo for every part. <hi>Britany</hi> ſomething defectiue in the Sunne, is refreſh't with the warmth of the ſea, flowing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13003:36"/>
round about it. <hi>Nilus</hi> tempers the drought of <hi>Egypt, Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> husbands <hi>Meſopotamia, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> is reported to ſowe &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> If you come into a houſe, and ſee the excellent culture, order, and ornaments of it; you cannot but thinke ſome Maſter rules there much better then all the furniture. So in this houſe of the world, when you ſee the heavens and the earth, their provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, order, and law; belieue there is a Lord of this vniuerſe, and a Father more excellent then the Starres, and all the parts of it. Except peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe there is no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of providence, you will thinke it a matter of enquiry, whether the celeſtiall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13003:37"/>
be governed by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of one, or the will and pleaſure of many; which thing tis not much labour to open vnto a man, who will conceiue the nature of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires on earth, which likely haue their example from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. When did ſociety of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire here either beginne with faith, or end without blood? I omit the <hi>Perſians</hi> inaugura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting principality by the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of horſes, and I paſſe over the almoſt forgotten fable of the <hi>Theban</hi> brothers. The ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and contention of <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Remus</hi> for a kingdome of ſheepeheards, and a cottage, is well knowne. The warres of the Father and Sonne in law, are ſpoken of through the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13003:37"/>
whole world, and the fortune of ſo great an Empire, could not ſatiſfie theſe two. See the reſt. There is one King of the Bees, one leader among the flockes, one chiefe in the heardes: and can you thinke the great principality of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to bee divided, and the whole power of the true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Empire, to be cut in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? when tis apparant that God the parent of all things hath neither beginning nor ending: which giues natiuity to all, perpetuity to himſelfe: which was before the world a world of contemplation to himſelfe, who by his word commandes a being to all things that are, by an infinite reaſon, and vertue diſpoſes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13003:38"/>
and perfects the vniuerſe. He cannot bee ſeene, for our eyes cannot endure his brightneſſe; he cannot bee comprehended, hee is too pure for our feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; hee cannot bee brought into eſtimation, hee is greater then our ſenſes; infinite, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mense, and only to himſelfe ſo great, as he only knowes. our breaſt is too narrow to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him: and therefore wee can only deeme worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of him when we ſay hee is ineſtimable. I will ſpeake what I thinke. Who weenes to know the greatneſſe of God, doth diminiſh it, he that will not diminiſh it, muſt confeſſe himſelfe ignorant of it. Neither aske you the name of God, God is the name.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13003:38"/>
There words of appellation are vſefull, where a multitude is to bee ſeverally knowne one from another, by their proper <hi>Heraldrie.</hi> To God who is alone, the whole title is God: whome if I ſhall call Father, you may thinke him earthly: if King, you may ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him carnall: if Lord, you may alſo apprehend him mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. Take away theſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of names, and you ſhall better ſee his glory. All mens conſent is of him. I heare the people when they lift vp their hands to Heaven, ſay nothing but, God: and God is great, and God is true, and if God permit; is this the ſpeach of an ordinary <hi>Plebeian,</hi> or the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of a Chriſtian confeſſing his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13003:39"/>
beliefe? And they who wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue <hi>Iupiter</hi> Prince of heaven they are deceiued in the name but they agree vpon the vnity of power. Alſo I heare th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Poets preaching one Fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Gods and men: and making the mindes of all mortall men ſuch only, as it pleaſeth God the Father of all things to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. Whence the <hi>Mantuan Maro</hi> plainely, neerely and truely, where hee ſaith,— Firſt Heaven and earth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part beſide—Are with an inward ſpirit fed—and an infuſed minde—doth ſtirre them vp, with every kinde of creatures. The ſame in another place doth call this minde and ſpirit God. — For the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is — diffuſed through
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13003:39"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth through ſeas and lofty kyes, — From hence all beaſts and men, all ſhowres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd fires. And what other thing doe wee preach God to bee, but a minde, a reaſon, a ſpirit? Let vs rehearſe if you pleaſe the learning of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. You ſhall find them although in a diverſe way, conſpiring to deliuer the ſame doctrine. I omit thoſe of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique ruder times, who for their ſayings were reputed wiſe men. Let <hi>Thales Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> bee the firſt who diſputed of things celeſtiall. Hee ſaid that water was the beginning of things, and God that minde which formed all things out of water, a minde too high and ſublime for humane appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13003:40"/>
proceeding from God. See the principall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers opinion altogether conſonant with ours. <hi>A naxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes</hi> afterwards, and then the <hi>Apollonian Diogenes</hi> make the aire God, infinite and without meaſure, here is alſo their conſent of divinity. In <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agoras</hi> his deſcription, a kind of infinite minde is called God. To <hi>Pythagoras</hi> God is a ſpirit paſſing and intentiue through the whole nature of things, from which the life of all cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures is taken. <hi>Xenophanes</hi> will haue God to be a minde, and all beſides that is infinite. <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> hath many popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Gods, but for a naturall chiefe God he knowes one only. <hi>Spouſippus</hi> will haue
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13003:40"/>
God to be a naturall, anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vigor, by which all things are governed. And <hi>Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> although he be the firſt inventor of atomes, yet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually he cals God, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and intelligence which doth powre forth ſo many i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of it ſelfe. <hi>Straton</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deifies nature. And that <hi>Epicurus</hi> who faines the Gods either idle or none, yet giues he a ſupremacy to nature. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> is various, yet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes one power; ſometimes he ſayes the minde is God, on while the world, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he makes God ouerſeer of the world. Alſo the <hi>Pontick Heraclides</hi> aſcribes vnto God a divine minde though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly. <hi>Theophraſtus, Zenon,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13003:41"/>
Cryſippus</hi> and <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> they be alſo divers, yet they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vpon a vnity of proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. In <hi>Cleanthes</hi> diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſometimes the minde, ſometimes the ſpirit, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the ethereall part is God. <hi>Zenon</hi> his maſter will haue a naturall diuine lawe, or that ethereall part, and ſometimes reaſon, to be the beginning of all things. The ſame man interpreting <hi>Iuno</hi> to be the aire, <hi>Iupiter</hi> the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, <hi>Neptune</hi> the ſea, <hi>Vulcan</hi> the fire, &amp; likewiſe ſhewing the other Gods of the people, to bee the Elements, doth ſhrewdly convince &amp; reproue the publique error. <hi>Chryſippus</hi> almoſt after the ſame manner belieues a divine virtue, a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13003:41"/>
nature, the world ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ſometimes a fatall neceſſity, to be God: and hee followes <hi>Zenon,</hi> in a naturall interpretation vpon the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems of <hi>Heſiod, Homer,</hi> and <hi>Orpheus.</hi> The <hi>Babilonian Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogenes</hi> alſo hath a way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding and ſhewing that the birth of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the riſing of <hi>Minerua,</hi> import things and not Deities. For the <hi>Socrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Xenophon</hi> denies that the forme of the true God can be ſeene, and therefore ought not to be ſought after. <hi>Ariſto</hi> of <hi>Chios</hi> ſayes, he cannot be comprehended. Both theſe conceiued a divine Maieſty by their diſpaire of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it. <hi>Platoes</hi> diſcourſe of God is more cleare, both for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13003:42"/>
things and names, and it were indeed all heavenly, but that hee doth ſometimes debaſe it with mixture of a civill poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke perſwaſion. Wherefore in his dialogue of <hi>Timaeus,</hi> God is to him vnder that name the parent of the world, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the ſoule, the builder of all things both in Heaven and in earth; and he tels vs in his preface, that it is hard to finde him, by reaſon of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite incredible power, and when hee is found, no leſſe impoſſible to make a publique declaration of him. Theſe are almoſt the ſame things with ours: For we acknowledge a God, call him the parent of all things, and except wee bee demanded, wee vſe not to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13003:42"/>
make any vulgar ſpeach of him. I haue opened the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the moſt famous Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, all agreeing for one God, although vnder divers names: ſo as many would deeme, either the Chriſtians to bee now Philoſophers, or the Philoſophers to haue been then Chriſtians. Wherefore if the world bee ſo ruled by providence, and governed by the pleaſure of one God, the antiquity of ignorant people delighted and taken with their owne fables, ought not draw vs to a publique conſent of errour, refuted by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their owne Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, who haue on their ſide both reaſon and the authority of more auncient times. For
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13003:43"/>
our Anceſtors did ſo eaſily giue credence vnto lyes, as they did without examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on take vp into their beliefe many other prodigious mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, the divers ſhap'd mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Chimera,</hi> a <hi>Hidra</hi> happy to renew his heads by cutting off, <hi>Centau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> that is, Horſes bearing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſhapes of men: and whatſoever fame pleaſed to fanſie, they delighted to heare. What ſhall I ſpeake of thoſe Grandame tales, men turned into birds, wilde beaſts into men, men into trees and flowers? which things if they were done, thoſe things were done which are impoſſible and therefore were they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acted. And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13003:43"/>
our Anceſtors with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouident credulity, and rude ſimplicity did take Gods into their beliefe, whileſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly they worſhip their Kings, when after their death they deſire to ſee them in i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, when they reioice to detaine their memories in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, theſe ſolaces did in time grow to a holy ſolemnity. And every where before the world was open to commerce, when nations had not yet mingled their cuſtomes, every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, did worſhip their founder, or renowned Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, or chaſte Queene va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant aboue her ſexe, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who had found out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, or art, as citizens wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of remembrance. So the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13003:44"/>
dead had a reward and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an example. Read the writings of Hiſtorians, you will then confeſſe with me Gods created for merit of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or invention. <hi>Euhemerus</hi> purſues and numbers their birthes countries and ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and hee ſhewes all of them through ſeverall provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the <hi>Dictean Iupiter, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> of <hi>Delphos,</hi> the <hi>Pharian Iſis,</hi> and <hi>Eleuſinian Ceres:</hi> hee tels how they were aſſum'd into a reputation of Deity, who wandring through the earth did finde out new fruits for the better maintaining the life and liuely-hood of men. <hi>Perſeus</hi> plaies the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher to the ſame purpoſe, rehearſes the fruits which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13003:44"/>
were found and by whom vnder the ſame names; whence the <hi>Comedian</hi> ſporte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſaies, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Ceres</hi> will take colde. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great <hi>Macedonian</hi> writes in a famous letter to his Mother, that a Prieſt did for feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray vnto him the ſecret of the Gods being men only: hee makes <hi>Vulcan</hi> the chiefe of them all, and after him the race of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> Looke well vpon the hiſtory of <hi>Iſis,</hi> her tranſmutation into a ſwallow, her rattle, the ſcattered mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of thy <hi>Serapis</hi> or <hi>Oſiris,</hi> and his empty tombe, obſerue thoſe ſacred rites and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, you ſhall finde tragicall endings, deaths and funeralls,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13003:45"/>
mourning and lamentation of miſerable Gods. <hi>Iſis</hi> with her dogge-headed <hi>Anubis,</hi> and her bald Prieſts, doth with mournefull lamentation make enquiry for her loſt Sonne, and her wretched Prieſts beat their breſts and imitate the griefe of the vnhappy Mother. By and by they ſeeme to finde the litle infant, the Prieſts leap for ioy, her dogge-headed retriuer glories in his inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: neither doe they omit every yeare, eyther to looſe that which they finde, or finde that which they looſe. Is it not ridiculous to mourne that which you worſhip or to worſhip that for which you haue cauſe of mourning? Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe ſuch aunciently
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13003:45"/>
were the ſacred ceremonies of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> now vſe them. <hi>Ceres</hi> with burning torches, and girt about with Serpents, in much anxiety and ſorrow hunts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her daughter deflour'd and raviſhed as ſhe was wandring in the fields. Theſe are the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuſinian</hi> rites. And what bee <hi>Jupiters?</hi> A goate is the nurſe, and the infant is ſtolne away from his greedy Father, leaſt hee devoure him, and the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribant</hi> Prieſts make a great tinkling with bells, that the Father may not heare the ſquealing of the litle childe. I am aſhamed to ſpeake of the <hi>Dindimene Cybele,</hi> who being difformed and very old, as the Mother of many Gods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13003:46"/>
ſhe could not entice the vnhappily beautifull <hi>Atis</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to adultery, did cut out his ſtones, and make him an <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch</hi> God. For memory of this fable the <hi>Galli</hi> her capon Prieſts vnman themſelues and worſhip her with the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their body. Why, this is not ſanctimony but tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And what are the formes and habits of your Gods, is there not ridiculous ſcorne and diſgrace in them? <hi>Vulcan</hi> is a lame maimd God. <hi>Apollo</hi> through ſo many ages is ſtill a ſmooth chind God. <hi>Aeſcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> hath beard inough, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be the Sonne of the ever youthfull <hi>Apollo.</hi> Tis the blu-ey'd <hi>Neptune,</hi> the gray-ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Minerva,</hi> &amp; the goodly cow
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13003:46"/>
eyes of <hi>Iuno. Mercury</hi> hath wings on his feete, <hi>Pan</hi> hoofes and <hi>Saturne</hi> fetters, <hi>Ianus</hi> hath two faces as if hee went contrary waies. The huntreſſe <hi>Diana</hi> is high girt, and armed with jauelins, <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> hath many breaſts, and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> of the high waies hath three heads, and makes a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſhew with a multitude of hands. And for your <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſometimes his ſtatue is beard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſometimes he is ſet vp with a huge beard: when hee is called <hi>Hammon,</hi> then hee weares hornes, when <hi>Capito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus,</hi> his right arme beares a thunderbolt, when <hi>Latiall,</hi> hee is all embrued in blood, and when <hi>Feretrius,</hi> come not neare him. And not to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13003:47"/>
dwell longer vpon theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts of <hi>Iupiters,</hi> there bee ſo many monſters of him, as names. <hi>Erigone</hi> is hung vp in a halter, to make the burning conſtellation of the Virgin amongſt the Starres. <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> haue made a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to liue and dye by turns every ſecond day. <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> that he may riſe vnto divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is ſtruck with thunder. <hi>Hercules</hi> that hee may put of his mortality, is burnt into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes vpon mount <hi>Oeta.</hi> Theſe fables and errours wee learne of our vndiſcerning parents, (and which is more grievous) they are our laborious ſtudy and diſcipline in the ſongs of the Poets; and it is a great wonder to ſee how much they
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13003:47"/>
haue blemiſh truth with their authority. Wherefore <hi>Plato</hi> in his inſtitution of a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth hath even baniſht <hi>Homer</hi> that renowned prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ever laureal Poet, from the number of his citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens. For this chiefe of Poets, in his <hi>Troian</hi> warre, makes a mocke of the Gods, and brings them every where into the actions and affaires of men. Hee ſets them together by the eares, wounds <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> bindes <hi>Mars,</hi> hurts and driues him out of the battaile. Hee tels how <hi>Iupiter</hi> is reskued by <hi>Briareus,</hi> when the other Gods conſpired to binde him, and how hee wept ſhowres of blood, becauſe hee could not deliuer his Sonne <hi>Sarpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:13003:48"/>
from death: and makes him bed his wife <hi>Iuno,</hi> through the helpe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> girdle, more luxuriouſly, then ever he had laine with any of his wenches. Otherwhere <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> hath the employment to ridde a ſtable of dung, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> is heardſman to <hi>Adme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; Neptune</hi> builds the wals of <hi>Troy</hi> for <hi>Laomedon,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy workeman hee cannot get his hire. There <hi>Vulcan</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his anvile beates out thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for <hi>Iupiter</hi> and armour for <hi>Aeneas:</hi> when heaven and thunder and lightning were long before ever <hi>Iupiter</hi> was borne in <hi>Creete;</hi> ſuch as that one-eyed <hi>Vulcan</hi> could never imitate, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelfe muſt ever feare. What ſhall
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13003:48"/>
I ſpeake of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> taken in adultery? and the rape of <hi>Jupiter</hi> vpon <hi>Ganimed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> conſecrated in heaven. All which things ſeeme to bee produced, that men may haue authority for their vices. With ſuch like inventions and ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lyes the diſpoſitions of youth are corrupted, on theſe fables they ſtay, and grow vp to a perfect age, and in theſe opinions they miſerably dye; when truth is more eaſily found, but of thoſe who ſeeke it. For all the writers of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times both Greeke and Latin haue deliuered that this <hi>Saturne</hi> Prince of all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous genealogie was a man. <hi>Nepos</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> in their hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory know this, and <hi>Thallus</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:13003:49"/>
and <hi>Diodorus</hi> ſpeake it. Hee for feare of his Sonnes rage fled from <hi>Creete,</hi> and came into <hi>Jtaly,</hi> and being hoſpital<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained by <hi>Ianus,</hi> taught many things to thoſe ignorant country people, as being a pretty poliſht <hi>Greeke,</hi> to write by Alphabet, to coyne mony, to make many ſorts of inſtruments. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had here ſafely lurkt, hee pleaſed to call this hiding place <hi>Latium.</hi> He gaue them a city called <hi>Saturnia,</hi> by his owne name, and <hi>Ianus</hi> left them his <hi>Ianiculum,</hi> for which they are both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred with poſterity. Therefore, when he ſo fled and lurkt out of the way, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he was both the father of a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13003:49"/>
man and a mans ſonne: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Jtalians</hi> cald a ſonne of heauen and of earth, becauſe he was to them of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne parents; as at this day when we ſee people ſuddenly come, and we know not from whence, we ſay they come from heauen, or obſcure igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble commers we doe terme ſonnes of the earth. This Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes ſonne hauing drouen his father out of <hi>Creete,</hi> raignd there, died there, and had children there: <hi>Iupiters</hi> caue is there yet to be ſeene, and they ſhew his ſepulcher, and many of their holy rites con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince his mortality. Tis idle to goe through all the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity and rablement of theſe Deities in a like narration;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13003:50"/>
when mortality proovd vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their firſt parents muſt of neceſſity fall on the reſt by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſucceſſion, except per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance you will faine them to be Gods after their death, as <hi>Romulus</hi> is a God by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie of <hi>Proculus,</hi> and tis the kind pleaſure of the <hi>Moores</hi> to haue <hi>Iuba</hi> be a God: and other Kings are Gods, which are conſecrated into Deitie, not becauſe the people belieued ſo, but to diſmiſſe them with honour from their office of kings craft. And many times theſe are made Gods againſt their will, they would rather ſtay in a mortality, they are afeard to be made Gods, and although they be never ſo old they would never willingly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13003:50"/>
be ſuch Gods, therfore of thoſe that die none be Gods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God cannot dye, and no Gods are borne, becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing muſt die that is borne, and that only is divine, which hath neither birth nor death, And if there were gods borne, why are not ſome borne in out dayes, except <hi>Iupiter</hi> be now waxed old, and <hi>Iuno</hi> hath left off teeming. And can <hi>Minerva</hi> grow gray headed before ſhe hath had children? Or is all this generation of Gods paſſed and gone, becauſe people no longer aſſent vnto their fables? But if Gods could be borne and not die, we ſhould haue more Gods then men, the heauens would not now bee large enough
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13003:51"/>
to containe them, the ayre could not receiue, nor the earth beare their multitudes. Whence it is manifeſt, that they were men, whoſe births we read, and whoſe deaths we know. When therefore the common people doe pray vnto their conſecrate images, and worſhippe them, who doubts but that ignorant opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is here deceiud with the beauty of the worke, dazeld with the bright glittering luſtre of gold and ſiluer, and beſotted on the faire whitenes of the Iron; But if a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in his minde with what torments and engines euerie image is formd, he will ſhame to feare that matter, which is ſo miſuſd by the artificer, before
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13003:51"/>
he can make it a God. For the wodden God, a peice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance of ſome vnhappy poſte or fireblocke, is hung vp, cut, ſquard, and hewed; the brazen or ſiluer God, (as it was often done by the <hi>Aegiptian</hi> king) is made out of ſome vncleane veſſell, knockt with hammers, brought into figure vpon the anvill: and the God of ſtone, is againe hewed, ſcrapd and made ſmooth by ſome impure vicious man. Theſe feele not the iniury of their natiuity, nor the honour of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe. Or perchance this ſtone, this wood, this ſiluer, is not yet a God. When then ſhall they be? They are now cemented, ſet together, ſet vp; is there yet no God? They
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13003:52"/>
haue their ornament, their conſecration, they are praied too. So at laſt a God is made when any man pleaſes to giue theſe ſtatues a dedication. Dumbe creatures, how much more truely doe they by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eſteeme of your Gods? Mice, Swallowes, Kites, they know theſe Gods haue no fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, they nibble them, get on top, &amp; ſet on them: &amp; if you driue them not away, they make neſts in the very mouth of your God. Spiders weaue cobwebbes about their face, they hang this worke on their heades: you wipe, cleanſe, and rubbe all of. And theſe Gods which you make, you protect and feare; whileſt none of you will conſider that you
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13003:52"/>
ought to know God before you worſhip him, whileſt men reioyce to obey their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents vnreaſonably, whileſt they had rather follow a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon errour then belieue themſelues, whileſt they know nothing of that they feare. So hath covetouſneſſe a conſecration in gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſo come idle ſtatues to finde their forme with you, ſo growes the <hi>Romane</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, whoſe rights if you runne through, how many things are there of laughter, and more of pitty? In the cold ſhriveling winter ſome courſe vp and downe naked, ſome goe capt after a ſtrange man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, carrying about on their ſhoulders targets, on
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13003:53"/>
ſome ſlaſh their skins, and from ſtreete to ſtreete leade their Gods a begging. You may not ſee ſome temples but once in the yeare, ſome not at all, ſome are not permitted to men, &amp; ſome are ſacred from women. Some holy ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies muſt be ſolemnized and crowned by a woman that knowes but one man, ſome by a common woman, &amp; ſhe is with great religious enquiry ſought for, which can number the moſt adulteries. Why, hee who makes libation with his owne blood, and ſupplicates with wounds, might he not be better prophane then religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſuch manner? And hee that cuts off his virilities with a ſhard, were hee not better
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13003:53"/>
violate the Gods then ſo pleaſe them? When if God would haue Eunuchs, hee ſhould not need your making, but might finde out a way of procreation for them. Who doth not by this vnderſtand, that if men were well in their wits, if they were ſound and entire of their ſenſes, they would not thus delude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. But common errour giues herein mutuall patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. The multitude of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding people is a Topick place of defence. Yet this ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion gaue Empire to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> it encreaſed them, it laid them a foundation of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture greatneſſe, raiſd not ſo much by vertue as by this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and piety? See if you
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13003:54"/>
pleaſe what kind of noble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous righteouſneſſe the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had in the beginning and cradle of their empire. In their firſt riſing were they not a ſelect band of wicked men, fortifiing and encreaſing themſelues with terror of their immanity? Their firſt company was collected by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting a place of ſanctuary for rogues; whither reſorted the deſperate, the criminal, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous, brothers of the blade, and traitors. And <hi>Romulus</hi> their generall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, that he might alſo be chiefe in villany, murdered his owne brother. Theſe are the firſt ſacraments of a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous city, and then to get them wiues againſt all civill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, they raviſh, violate,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13003:54"/>
delude neighbour virgins, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready betrothd or promiſed, and take many woemen from their bed of matrimony, with the parents and kindred of theſe they ioyne battell, and make effuſion of their blood. What is more irreligious, more bold, more preſuming of ſafety then a confidence of wickedneſſe? Now they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to driue out neighbours from their poſſeſſions, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne bordering cities, with their Temples and Altars: force the inhabitants to ioyne with them; by other mens harmes and their owne villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they get vp. And this diſcipline of <hi>Romulus,</hi> hath beene to their ſucceeding Kings and Captaines a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon patterne of example.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13003:55"/>
All that the <hi>Romans</hi> hold, that they poſſeſſe, and all their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies they owe to their ſhameles rapin. All their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are built from the ſpoiles of warre, the ruines of cities, the deſtruction of the Gods, and the ſlaughters of Prieſts. Is it not illuſion, and inſulting vpon the Gods, to obſerue thoſe religions which they haue beaten, and to haue them in adoration after they haue beene lead captiue in victory? For to worſhip that which you would ſubdue, is to conſecrate ſacriledge not Deities. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue the <hi>Romans</hi> beene as often impious as victorious, and they haue made ſo many ſpoiles of the Gods as they haue erected trophies over
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13003:55"/>
nations. Neither are the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> growne to greatnes with religion, but by being ſafely ſacrilegious. For how ſhould they obtaine from the Gods helpe in their warres, againſt whom they tooke armes, whom they droue out of their habitations, howſoeuer after they had lead them in triumph, they began to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them. Or what could theſe Gods doe for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> who had not power to preſerue againſt their armies the people amongſt whom they were aunciently wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped? And wee are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant what manner of natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Gods the <hi>Romans</hi> had. There was <hi>Romulus, Picus, Tiberinus,</hi> and <hi>Conſus,</hi> and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13003:56"/>
               <hi>Pilumnus,</hi> and <hi>Picumnus. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> both found out and did worſhip the privy Ladye <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acina. Hoſtilius</hi> found out feare and paleneſſe: then I know not by whom, the feaver had his dedication: ſuch was the ſuperſtition which was nouriſhed in that city as they did worſhip diſeaſes and indiſpoſitions of health. And indeed <hi>Acca Laurentia,</hi> and <hi>Flora,</hi> proſtitute ſhameleſſe queanes muſt alſo be compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the number both of their diſeaſes and Deities. And is it likely that ſuch Gods as theſe ſhould in diſpight of other Gods amongſt the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons dilate the Roman empire? (For indeed they, the <hi>Thraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Mars, Iupiter</hi> of <hi>Creete, Iuno</hi> of <hi>Argos,</hi> of <hi>Samos,</hi> of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:13003:56"/>
or <hi>Diana</hi> of <hi>Tauris,</hi> or the <hi>Idean</hi> Mother, or thoſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> rather prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies then Deities could not defend their owne people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Roman</hi> forces.) Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept peraduenture amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> the chaſtity of their Virgins was greater, and the religion of their Prieſts more holy, when frequently, many of their Virgins hauing eaſily made a fault with men without <hi>Veſtaes</hi> notice, haue had a civill revenge executed vpon their inceſt, and the reſt were more happy in wanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe then ſafe in chaſtity. And where doe your Prieſts more often hire fornications, treat Veneries, contriue adulteries, then at the altars, and images of the Gods. And no common
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:13003:57"/>
reſorts of whoererie doe ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſupply the buſineſſe of luſt, as the cells of thoſe, who are officers and guardians of the Temples. And yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe your Prieſts and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins were heard of in the world, at Gods pleaſure the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> had the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, the <hi>Medes,</hi> the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Greekes,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> when as yet they had none of your pontificall rites, no bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood of Prieſts to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the fields, no dauncing Prieſts in honour of <hi>Mars,</hi> no Virgins to attend the Godeſſe <hi>Veſta</hi> and her fire, no Prieſts of angurie, to keepe birds in coopes, to divine the ſucceſſe of things by their feeding or refuſall of meate. For now
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13003:57"/>
I am come to their examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which you ſay haue beene collected with great labour, not omitted without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ever obſerued with happy ſucceſſe. Will you ſay that <hi>Clodius, Flaminius</hi> and <hi>Jurius</hi> therefore loſt their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe they would not ſtay to know whether the barly falling on the ground did make an ominous leaping: yet <hi>Regulus</hi> obſerued this ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, and was taken by the enemies. <hi>Mancinus</hi> kept this religion, and yet was forct to yeelde to a baſe ſubmiſſion and captiuity. The chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken did eate for <hi>Paulus,</hi> and yet at the battaile of <hi>Cannae,</hi> both he and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of his army was cut
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13003:58"/>
downe. <hi>Caius Caeſar</hi> in ſpight of this divination forbidding him to ſaile into <hi>Affricke</hi> with his fleete before winter, put forth, and had a faire paſſage with victory. As for your ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, how ſhall I purſue their hiſtory? <hi>Amphiaraus</hi> after his death makes anſweares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things to come, and yet was he ignorantly betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to death by his wife for the loue of a gold chaine. Blinde <hi>Tireſias</hi> muſt ſee things future, who could not diſcerne any thing before him. Old <hi>Ennius</hi> faines anſweares of the <hi>Pithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Apollo</hi> for King <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> when <hi>Apollo</hi> had long before left of to bee a poeticall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Whoſe wary doubtfull oracle quickly ceaſ'd, when
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13003:58"/>
men began to bee more civill and leſſe credulous. And <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> knowing the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of ſuch anſweares, did complaine that the <hi>Pythian</hi> Virgin Propheteſſe, was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by King Philip. But you will ſay that theſe auguries and theſe oracles did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hit on the truth. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indeed chance may ſometimes ſeeme in many lyes to ſpeake as it were to purpoſe, yet I will trie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover this fountaine of errour and wickedneſſe, to ſhew whence all this diſguiſe hath riſen, I will even open the very foundations, and lay them to a manifeſt view. There bee falſe ſpirits wandring vp and downe ſince with terreſtriall
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:13003:59"/>
corruptions and deſires they loſt their celeſtiall vertue. Theſe ſpirits haue fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone the puritie of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with a burden and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of vices, and to comfort their calamitie, being ruin'd themſelues they neuer leaue to attempt the diſtruction of others, to infuſe a depravation of errour, by inducing evill religions to alienate with themſelues ſo many as they can from the true ſervice of God. The Poets acknowledge theſe to bee cunning ſpirits, Philoſophers diſpute of them, <hi>Socrates</hi> was not ignorant of them, who at the direction and will of one ſtill preſent with him, did decline or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake buſineſſe. The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13003:59"/>
alſo doe not only know them, but act all the ſport of miracles by their helpe. By their inſpiration and infuſion they worke impoſtures, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things appeare which are not, and thoſe things not apeare which are. Of theſe Magicians <hi>Hoſtanes</hi> the chiefeſt both for ſpeech and deed, doth attribute vnto the true God his deſerued maieſty, and makes honourable mention of his angells, that is his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who tremble at his word and countenance, he alſo makes mention of thoſe other cunning wandring terreſtiall ſpirits enemies to mankind. And <hi>Plato</hi> who thought it ſo great a buſineſſe to finde out God, doth eaſily diſcouer both
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13003:60"/>
theſe vnto vs, and in his feaſting dialogue ſtriues to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their nature. He will haue them to be a middle ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betwixt ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, halfe mortall, halfe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, compounded with a mixture of terreſtiall heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and celeſtiall lightneſſe. He will haue them cauſe in us the firſt incentiue ſparkes of loue, to informe and ſlide into mens breſts, to mooue their ſenſes, faſhion their affections, and then powre in a fiery heate of luſt. Wherefore theſe vncleane ſpirits (as the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> ſhew) lurke vnder con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat ſtatues and images, and by an inſpiration doe gaine with people authority to be
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13003:60"/>
reputed Gods, whiles they ſometimes ſeeme to poſſeſſe their prophets, to abide in temples, to animate the liuers of the ſacrifice, to gouerne the flights of birds, rule lotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and deliuer oracles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volu'd with much falſhood. For they are deceiud and doe deceiue, as not knowing truth ſincerely, nor confeſſing that which they know, to their owne perdition. So doe they draw vs from heauen, and call us from the true God vnto theſe materiall things: They diſorder our life, trouble our dreames, creepe ſecretly into our bodies, as being thinne ſpirits, forge diſeaſes, terrify mindes, diſtort members, that they may force us to a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13003:61"/>
of them, when after a ſacrifice of beaſts, and feaſting at their altars, they ſeeme to be appeaſed, and releaſe, and cure thoſe whom they had affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Theſe are alſo the cauſes of thoſe mad men whom you ſee breake forth into the ſtreetes. Their owne Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets alſo are ſometimes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt when they are forth the temple, they roule their heads and rage. Theſe ſpirits incite both, although to a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe purpoſe. And from them proceede thoſe things of which you haue before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, when <hi>Iupiter</hi> cauſd a new celebration of ſports accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a dreame, when the little ſhip did follow the matrones girdle, when the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:13003:61"/>
were ſeene with their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſes. The moſt of you doe know, that theſe ſpirits con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ſo much of themſelues, as often, as by vs with tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of wordes and fire of praiers they are driuen out of bodies. <hi>Saturne</hi> himſelfe and <hi>Serapis</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and all the the reſt of your Gods whom you worſhip, are with griefe commanded to ſpeake what they are plainly. Neither would they lye to there owne diſgrace, eſpecially when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you are preſent. When they doe thus confeſſe truth of themſelues, then belieue from there owne witneſſe that they are euill ſpirits. when we coniure them by the only true God, they hardly
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13003:62"/>
ſtay in poſſeſt bodyes, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſently leape forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vaniſh by degrees, as the fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the patient helps, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grace of Gods miniſter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes, So doe they ſhunne the preſence of Chriſtians, whom a farre of they prouoke in your rioting aſſemblies. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inſinuating themſelues into the affections of vndiſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning people, they dare but pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily incite you to a hatred of vs through feare. For tis naturall to hate whom we feare, and to doe all the miſchiefe wee can vpon thoſe, of whom we ſeeme to ſtand in danger. So doe they foreſtall your mindes and ſhut vp your breaſts from right vnderſtanding, that men vndertake to hate vs before
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13003:62"/>
they know what we are, leaſt knowing, they ſhould either follow our example, or leaue off to purſue our condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But how great a crime it is to paſſe ſentence vpon men vnknowne, vntried, which you doe, belieue our earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. For wee were as you are, and in a blinde ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidneſſe wee thought as you: that Chriſtians did worſhip monſters, devoure Infants, make inceſtuous banquets; neither would wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that theſe fables were ſtill talkt of, but never ſearcht vnto proofe, when never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was found to giue evidence herein, although he was ſure to haue pardon for the fact, and favour for the inditement.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13003:63"/>
And ſurely this crime impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Chriſtians was ſo nothing, as any of them brought in queſtion of his faith, did neither bluſh at it, nor feare, only repenting that hee had not beene a Chriſtian ſooner. Yet wee who did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to defend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in iudgement, perſons ſacrilegious, inceſtuous, and even <hi>Parricides,</hi> were of minde that theſe Chriſtians ought not to bee heard ſpeake for themſelues. And many times as it were out of pitty did vſe on them ragefull cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, to force a deniall of their beliefe, that they might not dye; vſing in theſe things a moſt perverſe triall, not to cleare truth but to extort
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13003:63"/>
falſhood, when if any did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelfe a Chriſtian through infirmity, overpreſt and vanquiſhed with tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wee did favour him preſently, as if ſuch deniall and abiuring had made ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient expiation for all his faults. Doe you not ſee your owne thoughts and actions in vs? When if reaſon had beene iudge, and not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of thoſe evill ſpirits, theſe men ſhould rather haue beene vrged to confeſſe their inceſts, adulteries, impious ceremonies, and immolation of Infants, then to vnſay their Chriſtianity. For with thoſe fables haue your ſpirits filled the eares of ignorant people to raiſe in them a horrible exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13003:64"/>
of vs: But no wonder if you doe not here vrge the queſtion, ſince fame which is nouriſhed by diſperſion of lies periſheth at the declaration of truth. Such is the buſineſſe of your ſpirits: they did ſow, they did foment this moſt falſe rumour; and from thence it is that you heare, our divine ſecrecie ſhould bee an Aſſes head. Who would bee ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh as to worſhip this? Or who is not more foole to haue this imagination of vs, but that you doe all-over conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate your ſelues for Aſſes, by worſhipping the Lady <hi>Epona</hi> in your ſtable, and ſacrificing the ſame Aſſes religiouſly, to your Goddeſſe <hi>Iſis?</hi> Oxe heads alſo and the heads of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13003:64"/>
weathers you both ſacrifice and worſhip. You dedicate Gods in ſhape halfe goates and halfe men, halfe Lions and halfe dogges; and doe you not with the <hi>Egyptians</hi> both wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and feede the heyfer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis?</hi> Neither doe you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne their other religious rites appointed to ſerpents crocodiles, beaſts, birds, and fiſhes; and if any kill a God of theſe, hee muſt by the law ſuffer death. The ſame <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> with many of your ſelues, doe not feare <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> more, then you alſo feare the acrimony of <hi>Oignions,</hi> nor more trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at <hi>Serapis,</hi> then a crack ſent forth at our neither hole. Alſo hee who tales it forth, that wee worſhip the vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13003:65"/>
of our Prieſt, doth but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to put on vs their owne brutiſh behauiour. For theſe may well bee their ſacred ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, with whom all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe is called vrbanity: who envie the licentiouſneſſe of the ſtewes, who licke mens privities, and with a libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous mouth muzzle in ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parts. Whoſe tongues are nought in ſilence, who are ſooner weary then aſhamed of their immodeſty. O the horrible ſinne! they admit that voluntary filthineſſe in themſelues, which younger age cannot brook, nor the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt ſlaue bee forced vnto. Theſe like ordurs, it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs to heare, &amp; many of vs dare not be of counſell with
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13003:65"/>
ſuch offenders. And you faine theſe vnworſhipfull thinges of our chaſter modeſtye, which we could neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue poſſible amongſt men, except you did proue them vpon your ſelues. Alſo where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you aſcribe vnto our adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a man criminall and his croſſe, in a nearenes and borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of truth you looſe your ſelues farre away to thinke, that with vs a criminall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might deſerve, or a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man might obtaine to bee eſteemed a Deity. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, hee is a man moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, whoſe hope leanes vpon mortality, and whoſe helpe muſt needs periſh in a mans death. Indeed the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> ſomewhere make
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13003:66"/>
choice of a man whom they may worſhip, him alone they make propitious, him they conſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, to him they offer ſacrifice; yet hee who is thus a God to others, feeles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a man, whether hee will or no: neither can hee in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding the conſcience of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, deceiue his owne. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnto Princes and Kings, not as to great and choice men (for this is lawfull) but as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods, your flattery doth ſhamefully giue adoration; when to a right worthy man, honour more truly, and to an excellent good man, loue more ſweetly is due. So they call on their Deity, ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their ſtatues, implore his Genius, that is, his ſpirit: and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13003:66"/>
ſafer it is with you to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare by <hi>Iupiter</hi> then the Genius of a King. Croſſes we neither worſhip nor pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. But clearely, you who conſecrate Gods of wood, doe peraduenture adore woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den croſſes, as parts of your Gods. For your enſignes, and your Eagle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and banners of the armies, what are they but guilded and adorned croſſes? Your victorious trophies haue not only the ſimilitude of a ſimple croſſe, but they imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the very perſon of a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified man. Indeed naturally we ſee in a ſhippe the ſigne of a croſſe, when ſhe is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnder full ſayles, or when ſhe glides along with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panſion of oares, and when
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13003:67"/>
the tongue of a waine or the ſweape of a coatch is erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there is the ſigne of the croſſe; likewiſe, when a man ſpreading out his hands to heaven doth with pure minde beſeech Gods mercy ſo are your reaſonable occaſions, or your religions formed with the croſſes ſigne. Now I would willingly meete with that man, who either ſaies or belieues that we are initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with the ſlaughter or blood of an infant. Doe you thinke it poſſible, that our hearts ſhould bee ſo hard as to wound mortally ſuch tender litle members? Can any man be ſo ſavage as to ſtrike, powre out, and exhauſte the halfe blood of a young tender child,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:13003:67"/>
that is ſcarce yet mankinde? No man can belieue this but ſuch a one as dares doe it. For I ſee you expoſe vnto beaſts and birds, children begotten by your ſelues, ſometimes with a lamentable ſort of death ſtrangle the litle chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. There bee Mothers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you who in their own bowels doe with potions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the hope of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and make a Parricide before they haue brought it forth, &amp; theſe things are from the diſcipline of your Gods. For <hi>Saturne</hi> did not expoſe, but devoure his Sonnes: wherefore in ſome parts of <hi>Affrick,</hi> children are to him ſacrificed by their parents, kiſſing and colling the Infants
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13003:68"/>
ſportfully, that the ſacrifice may not be with lamentation. It was a cuſtome with the <hi>Pontick Taurians</hi> and the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Buſiris</hi> to kill ſtrangers in ſacrifice, and with the <hi>Gaules</hi> to make humane or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inhumane oblations. The Romans did interre in the earth a liue ſacrifice of a <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> man and woman, with <hi>Gaules</hi> likewiſe, and at this day the latiall <hi>Iupiter</hi> is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped with homicide: And that which well enough be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemes the ſonne of <hi>Saturne,</hi> a wicked and criminall man, he is glutted with blood. Peraduenture hee taught <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyline</hi> to league his coniurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in blood, to imbrue with mans blood the Goddeſſe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13003:68"/>
               <hi>Bellona:</hi> and with the blood of a man to heale the falling ſickneſſe ſeemes his preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a cure greater then the diſeaſe. Nor are they much leſſe barbarous, who from the publique ſand taking beaſtes bedaubd and infected with the blood, garbidge and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of men, haue the ſtomack to devoure them. Tis not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs to ſee homicide, nor heare it, and wee are ſo afeard of humane blood, that even our tables know no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice made with the blood of beaſtes. And that fable of an inceſtuous banquet is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a lie forgd at a conſultation of your ſpirits, to maculate the glory of our chaſte life with an averſion of ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13003:69"/>
infamy; with the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of it to keepe men off from enquiring the truth. And your <hi>Fronto</hi> delivers not this as a witneſſe but as an oratour, to raiſe vpon vs a contumelious aſperſion. Theſe are things more properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to your owne ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: it is amongſt the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> ſufferable by law for children to mingle with their Mothers; with the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Athenians,</hi> brothers and ſiſters marrie legally. Your Annalls and tragedies glorie in inceſts, which you willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read and heare: and ſo you worſhip inceſtuous Gods, who haue laine with Mother, daughter, and ſiſter. Inceſt is therefore often deprehended
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:13003:69"/>
amongſt you, and ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: alſo many times you may vnwillingly ruſh vpon theſe horrors, whileſt you ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your <hi>Venery</hi> promiſcuouſly, whilſt you every where ſowe children: whileſt alſo thoſe who are borne at home, you doe frequently expoſe to the mercy of ſtrangers, it is not poſſible but your luſt muſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten light vpon your owne children. So hauing your ſelues no conſcience of inceſt, you doe the more eaſily tie the fable of inceſt vpon our backs. But wee make our chaſtity good not only in ſhew but in minde alſo. We willingly containe our ſelues in the tye of one marriage. We haue a deſire of procreation only, or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:13003:70"/>
no deſire at all, we keepe our banquets not only modeſt but ſober. For we giue not our ſelues ouer to feaſting nor protract it with ſtrong drinke, we temper our mirth with gravity, with honeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and greater chaſtity of our bodyes: many doe rather enioy themſelues in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall virginity of an invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate body, then glory in it. In concluſion wee are ſo farre from inceſtuous luſt, as many doe even bluſh at a modeſt coniunction. Neither are wee preſently the raffe of people, if we refuſe your honours and purples: neither are wee ſqueamiſh in all things, if wee all be of one good minde, and and come together in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:13003:70"/>
with a quiet pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy: nor doe wee prate in corners, although you either ſhame or feare to heare vs in a publique aſſembly. And that our number doth every day encreaſe, it is no criminall imputatiom of errour, but a praiſe-worthy evidence of our truth. For a faire kinde of living doth both retaine vs, and invite others. Wee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne not one another by markes of body as you thinke, but by apparance of innocent and modeſt life. And that which grieues you to ſee, we liue in mutuall loue, becauſe wee know not how to hate: and ſo, to your envy, wee call one another brothers, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſervants of one God our
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13003:71"/>
Father, conſorts of faith, and coheires of hope; when you proudly doe diſdaine to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge others, and rage with mutuall hatred, neither owne any for brothers but by Parricide. But doe you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine wee hide our worſhip, becauſe wee haue no Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, no Altars? what image then would you haue vs frame for God, when if you rightly conſider, man himſelfe is Gods image? what Temple ſhall I build vnto him, when this whole world his worke cannot containe him? and and when I that am but a man reioice to liue more freely, ſhall I include the power of ſo great maieſty in a ſmall ſhrine? Is hee not much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13003:71"/>
in a dedication of our minde, in a conſecration of our inmoſt breaſt? What great or leſſe ſacrifice of beaſtes ſhall I offer to God, which he hath created for my vſe? This cannot bee a thing of gratefull acceptance; but the more winning oblation muſt bee a good intention, a pure minde and a ſincere conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Hee who loues inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, doth ſupplicate vnto God, hee that loues iuſtice, doth him libation, he that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaines from deceipt, makes God propitious, and whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſcues a man from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, makes the moſt glorious ſacrifice. Theſe are our ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, theſe are holy things with God: ſo hee with vs is
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13003:72"/>
moſt religious that is moſt iuſt. But wee doe not ſhew the God wee worſhip, nor doe wee ſee him? Nay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee belieue him to be a God, becauſe wee can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, though wee ſee him not. For in his workes and in all the motions of the world wee ever behold the preſence of his power: when hee thunders, when he ſends forth lightning, when he ſtrikes with thunder, when he cleares the aire. Neither ought you to wonder if you doe not ſee God. All things are driuen, hurld, and ſhaken with blaſts of winde, yet the wind, the blaſts, come not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our ſight. Hardly can wee endure to ſee the ſun which is cauſe of ſight to al, for his rayes
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13003:72"/>
keepe off our ſight and dimme the eyes of the beholder: and if you gaze on it any long while, it exſtinguiſheth the ſight. How then may you ſuſtaine the creator of the ſunne, the very fountaine of light; when from his light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and thunder you hide your felues? you will ſee God with your carnall eyes, when you cannot ſee your owne ſoule by which you liue and ſpeake. But God knowes not mens actions and being ſeated in heauen, either he ſurveyes not all, or he is ignorant in many particulars? O man thou doſt erre and art deceiued. How can God be farre off, when all things in heauen and earth, and things beyond this
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:13003:73"/>
province of the world are all full of God? he is euery where not only neere but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſd into vs. Looke againe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſunne he is fixt to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, yet he ſparkles himſelfe through all the earth, he is alike preſent euery where, and he is mingled with all things; for his cleareneſſe is never violated. How much more then muſt God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of all things, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer of all things, from whom there can be nothing ſecret, bee preſent in any darkneſſe, even in the greater darkneſſe of our thoughts. Wee doe not only liue vnder him, but as I had almoſt ſaid, we liue with him. Neither toye we an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument from the great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:13003:73"/>
of our ſelues: to our ſelues wee ſeeme many, but to him wee are but few. We diſtinguiſh kindreds and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: all this world is but one houſe to God. Kings know the affaires of their ſtate by the miniſtry of officers, God needs no intimation; we liue not only in his eyes but in his boſome: if you ſay that it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profitted the <hi>Jewes</hi> to worſhip this one God in the greateſt height of ſuperſtition with Altars and Temples, you erre out of ignorance, vnwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their ancient glory, and only minding their later cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. For as long as they worſhipped our God (who is the God of all) chaſtly, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently, religiouſly, as long as
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13003:74"/>
they obeyed his wholeſome precepts; of a few they were made innumerable, of poore rich, of ſlaues Kings; a few of them vnarmd, did puſue great flying armies and beare them downe, the very Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at Gods command fighting for them. Read over their ſtories, or if you are more pleaſd with the <hi>Romans</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to paſſe by the more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, ſee <hi>Flavius Ioſephus</hi> or <hi>Antonius Iulianus</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Iewes:</hi> you ſhall then finde that they deſerued their evill fortune by their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe: and that nothing happened vnto them which was not foretold, if they ſhould perſeuere in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. You ſhall perceiue
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:13003:74"/>
that they did firſt forſake God, before he forſook them; and that they were not as you impiouſly deliver, taken cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue with their Gods but by him yeelded vp, as men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking his diſcipline. As for the conflagration of the world, that fire ſhall fall on a ſuddaine; or to belieue this thing poſſible, it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon receiued opinion. And for the wiſer ſort of men, who of them doubts, who is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that all things which haue a beginning muſt haue an end, and all that is made muſt likewiſe periſh, and that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with all things contained in it muſt end as it beganne. Tis the conſtant opinion of the Stoicks, that the heavens
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:13003:75"/>
are nouriſhed with the exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of freſh and ſalt waters, and muſt paſſe away with a violence of fire, when all this world in a conſumption of the moiſture ſhall burne with flames. And for the conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Elements and the ruine of the world, the <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> are of the ſame minde. <hi>Plato</hi> ſaies the parts of the world are ſometimes drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with waters, ſometimes burnt with fire, and when hee ſaies, that the world was made perpetuall and never to bee diſſolued, yet he addes, that to Gods power it is both mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and periſhing. So then it is no wonder, if this great heape of things bee deſtroyed by him who pleaſd to make
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:13003:75"/>
it; &amp; Philoſophers diſpute the ſame things with vs; not that we follow their ſteps; but that they from the divine predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Prophets haue intermingled a ſhadow of truth in their writings. So alſo the chiefe of your wiſe men, firſt <hi>Pithagoras</hi> and eſpecially <hi>Plato</hi> deliuered though in a corrupt skant manner the condition of our liuing againe. For after a diſſolution of our bodies, they will haue our ſoules remaine perpetually, and make a diuers transmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into new bodies; and to diſtort the truth they adde, that the ſoules of men muſt returne into tame beaſtes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wilde beaſtes and birds. Certainly this their opinion
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:13003:76"/>
is not worthy the ſerious ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a Phloſopher, but reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the contumelious jeſting of a ſtage. But for our purpoſe tis enough that wiſe men doe in this alſo ſomewhat agree with vs. And can any bee ſo fooliſh or brutiſh, that he dare deny it as eaſie for God to reforme men anew, as to frame them in the beginning? Are they nothing after their death? So were they nothing before their being; as they were borne out of nothing, why may not they out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be repaired? Moreouer it muſt needs ſeeme more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to beginne that which was not, then to reiterate that which was. Doe you thinke that things periſh to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:13003:76"/>
they are withdrawne from the view of our eyes, every body whether hee bee dried into duſt, or diſſolued into water, or clodded into aſhes, or extenuated into va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, is taken indeed from vs, but may ſtill bee reſerued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God the keeper of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Neither doe wee as you thinke feare any loſſe in a ſepulture of fire, but wee frequent rather the more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and better cuſtome of interring, out of a civil conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. See how nature every where doth as it were for our comfort point out a future re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. The Sun drownes it ſelfe in the waues, and riſes againe, the ſtarres ſlide away, and returne, the flowers dye
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:13003:77"/>
and ſpring againe. The buſhes caſt their leaues, and againe grow greene, and ſeedes if they doe not rotte cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a new growth: ſo our bodies like trees in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they hide their greeneſſe in a drie diſguiſe. Why doe you make ſuch haſt, will you haue trees renew their green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the depth of winter? So muſt our bodies expect their ſpring. And I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that many out of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their ill deſeruings, doe rather wiſh to bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing after death then belieue it: for they had rather bee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly extinguiſht, then returne to a reparation of torments. Theſe mens errour is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſd by the licentiouſneſſe
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:13003:77"/>
Of the world and the great patience of God, whoſe iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the more ſlowe it is, the more iuſt it will be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet are they put in remembrance by the books of the moſt learned men, and the poets verſes, of a fierce floud and the often circling heate of the Stigian lake prepared for eternall puniſhments, as the tradition is from their ſpirits owne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and the oracles of the prophets. And therefore <hi>king Iupiter</hi> himſelfe he ſweares religiouſly by thoſe fierce tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and the blacke gulfe, at which ordained for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of him and his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers he trembles before hand, ſeeing theſe torments haue neither meaſure nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:13003:78"/>
There the wiſe fire burnes the body &amp; reſtores it, it rends and repares: as the flames of lightning blaſt the body and not conſume it, as the fires of <hi>Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius,</hi> and other burning earths, ſtill flame and ſpend not: ſo that penall fire is not fed with the empairing of thoſe that are burnt, but nouriſht with the everlaſting torture of their bodies. And that they are thus worthily tormented for impious and vniuſt, who doe not know God, none but a profane man can call in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; when it is no leſſe ſinne not to know, then to offend the Father and Lord of all things. And although not knowing God bee ſufficient
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:13003:78"/>
cauſe for puniſhment, as the knowing him may availe for pardon, yet if wee Chriſtians for point of life bee compared with you, howſoeuer your diſcipline in many things is beyond ours, wee ſhall bee found aſſuredly the better men. For you forbid adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and doe them: wee only in this kind are knowne men by our wiues. You puniſh crimes committed, with vs thoughts are guilty. You feare others that are conſcious of your ſinnes, we feare our own conſcience, without whoſe peace wee cannot enioy our ſelues. In briefe the priſons are fild with your numbers; there is no Chriſtian but whom you make guilty of his
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:13003:79"/>
religion, or who hath depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from this. Nor let any man ſeeke comfort or excuſe for his ſinnes in deſtiny. For if there were a God of deſtiny as you enſhrine him, yet the minde is free, and the action not the perſon of a man muſt ſuffer iudgement. And what is deſtiny but that which God hath foreſpoken of vs? Who when he might foreknow our conditions, hath determined of every one of vs, according to our merits &amp; quality. So is not our natiuity condemned, but puniſhment is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ill nature of our diſpoſition. And thus in few words enough of deſtiny, of which I haue more largely and truly diſputed in another
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:13003:79"/>
place. Then whereas you ſay the greateſt part of vs are poore, this is not our infamy but glory: for as the minde growes diſſolute in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, ſo it is confirmed with frugality. Yet who can be accounted poore who doth not want, who gapes not after the goods of other men, who is rich towards God? He is the moſt poore, who when he hath much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires more. And I will ſpeake as I thinke: no man can bee ſo poore as hee is borne. The birds liue without a patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the beaſtes looke but for their daily food: yet theſe are made for vs, and if wee covet not at all theſe things, wee poſſeſſe them. Therefore as
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:13003:80"/>
he that travailes a iourny, goes beſt that goes lighteſt, ſo in this waifaring life he is more happy that eaſily beares his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, then he which pantes with the burden of riches. And yet if we deemed riches vſefull, we might aske them of God, and hee may out of indulgency beſtow ſomething on vs. But we had rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe riches then be their jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous keepers. We rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire innnocency, and earneſtly begge patience of him, wee had rather be good then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall: and if wee feele and ſuffer in our bodies the caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of mankinde, this is not a puniſhment, but an excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. For valour is hardened with infirmities, and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:13003:80"/>
is often the Mother of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And in briefe the ſtrength both of body and minde doth languiſh without laborious excerciſe, and all your valiant men whom you praiſe for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, they haue moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht in memory for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous bearing of their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. God therefore who is the ruler of all, and who dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loues thoſe that bee his, doth not deſpiſe vs, and hee is able to giue preſent helpe, although hee ſeeme to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare. For in adverſities hee ſearches and tries our reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in dangers hee weighs our diſpoſitions, even to the laſt hazard of death he queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the wills of men, being ſecure that nothing can periſh
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:13003:81"/>
from him, and as gold with fire, ſo are we approued by hard encounters. What a faire ſpectacle it is for God, when a Chriſtian enters the liſts with griefe, compoſes an endurance againſt threates, puniſhments, and torments? When with laughter hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultes vpon the hurrie of death and horrour of execution, when he erects his liberty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Kings and Princes, yeelds only to God, to whom he belongs? When like a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant victor he glories o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the iudge that pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces his ſentence: and victory it is, when a man hath atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that he ſought for. What ſouldier will not more boldly provoke danger vnder the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:13003:81"/>
eyes of the Generall? For none can haue rewardes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee hath given experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of himſelfe: and yet a Generall cannot giue that which he hath not; he cannot prolong life, though hee can honour a ſouldiers worth. But the ſouldier of God, is neither forſaken in his paine, nor endes his life in death, and may bee thought but never found miſerable. You your ſelues doe praiſe calamitous men vnto the heavens, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, <hi>Mutius Scae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vola</hi> who when he had miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his attempt vpon the King, had died amongſt his enemies if he had not ſhowne vnto them ſuch an example of courage in the burning of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:13003:82"/>
his right hand. And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our men haue endured without out-cries the burning vnto aſhes not of their right hand only but their whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, when it was in their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by deniall of their beliefe to be let goe, and liue freely? Doe I compare the men of ours with <hi>Mucius,</hi> with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilius,</hi> with <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gulus?</hi> The very Children and woemen among vs by an inſpired pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of griefe, doe deſpiſe and laugh at your croſſes, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> torments, your wilde beaſtes, and all your contemptible terrours of puniſhment. And you miſerably will not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that no man would, either without great reaſon vndergoe, or could without
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:13003:82"/>
Gods aide abide ſuch tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Except that deceiue you, becauſe men not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God doe flow in riches, flouriſh in honours, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in power. Vnhappy men, theſe are raiſd high, that their fall may bee greater: like ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices they are fatted vnto puniſhment, and like beaſtes are crownd for ſlaughter. Some of them are for this lifted vp vnto Empires and domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that they may ſell the diſpoſitions of their wicked ſoules vnto all licentiouſneſſe of free power. For without the knowledge of God what ſolid felicity can there be; which paſſes like a dreame, and ſlides away almoſt before it is poſſeſt. Art thou a King?
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:13003:83"/>
Thou doſt feare as thou art feared: and although thou bee guarded with great retinue, yet art thou but one man ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to infinite dangers. Art thou rich? But fortune is deceitfull of truſt, and with great proviſion the ſhort jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of life is rather burdened then inſtructed. Doſt thou glory in thy purples and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of dignity? Tis a vaine errour of men, and an empty pompe to ſhine in purple, and be ſordid in the minde. Art thou deſcended from aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent nobility? Thou doſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in but praiſe thy parents: yet are wee all borne of equall condition, and in truth only diſtinguiſhed by vertue. We therefore who make our eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:13003:83"/>
only by manners and modeſt behauiour, abſtaine willingly from your evill pleaſures, your evill pompes, and ſpectacles: the beginnings of which wee know to bee vnholy, and the continuance full of damnable allurements. For in your racing ſports with chariots, who would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the mad conteſtation of your peoples part taking? In your fencers, who doth not abhorre a diſcipline of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? In your ſtage ſports there is no leſſe fury, and more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenity, for now the actor doth either dilate adulteries or preſent them, now in a wanton manner faining loue he puts the ſpectators into earneſt luſt: and then diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:13003:84"/>
your Gods by perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their adulteries, their lamentations, their hatreds, then with diſſembled griefes, vaine geſtures and feares hee provokes your teares. So in a lye you bewaile the deathes of men and loue to behold them in a true execution. And if wee ſhare not the reliques of your ſacrificing feaſtes, and the goblets which are firſt powrd forth vnto your idols, this is no confeſſion of feare, but an aſſertion of true liberty. For although every thing that growes as being the inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gift of God cannot by your miſſuſance bee condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: yet we abſtaine, leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould thinke we did by this yeelde our ſelues ſubiect
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:13003:84"/>
vnto your ſpirits, or that wee were ſomething aſhamed of our owne religion. And who is he that doubts whether we doe refreſh our ſelues with the flowres of the ſpring, when wee take the roſe and the lilly, and whatſoeuer elſe in flowres hath faireneſſe of ſmell and colour; with theſe looſe and ſoft wee ſtrowe our houſes, and with ſome bound vp wee fill our boſomes. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you muſt pardon vs if wee crowne not our heads with them. For we vſe to draw the ayre of a ſweete flower with our noſtrills, not with our haire and hinder parte of our head. Neither do we put garlands vpon the dead. Rather in this wee
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:13003:85"/>
wonder at you, why you ſhould giue vnto the dead who feele nothing, your torches and your coronets of f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owres, when if he be happy he now wantes them not, and miſery cannot reioice in flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. But we prepare our buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls in the ſame tranquility with which wee liue. Wee put not on them a fading crowne, but wee expect for them a crowne ever freſh with eternall flowres: wee vſe the liberality of our God with moderation, and ſecure in the hope of future felicity, we are encouragd in confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his Maieſty ever preſent with vs. So wee riſe againe to happineſſe, and wee in a pleaſing contemplation
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:13003:85"/>
of what we ſhall be. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let <hi>Socrates</hi> your gibing <hi>Athenian</hi> looke to it, who hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourd himſelfe in a confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of knowing nothing, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee be glorious in the iudgement of a moſt falſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Let <hi>Arceſilas, Carneades,</hi> and <hi>Pyrrho,</hi> and all the <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demick</hi> multitude perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliberate, let alſo <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi> ſtill put off his reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; we contemne the browes of the Philoſophers, whom we know to haue beene cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters of youth, and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and <hi>Tyrants,</hi> and ever e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent againſt their owne vices. Wee who pretend not wiſdome by a ſtrange habit, but an integrity of minde, doe not ſpeake but liue in a great
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:13003:86"/>
manner: wee glory to haue found that which they ſought with great ambition &amp; could not obtaine. Why are we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull? Why are we envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to our ſelues, if the true knowledge of divinity hath come to be ripely apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our age? Let vs enioy our bleſſing, &amp; let vs be tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in a right vnderſtanding: Let ſuperſtition be reſtraind, impiety be expiated, true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be preſerud. When <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> had ended his oration, for a while wee in an amazd ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence did fixe our eyes vpon him; and as for my ſelfe, I almoſt knew not where I was through an exceſſe of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whereas hee had with arguments, examples, and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:13003:86"/>
authorities of reading beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deliuered thoſe things, which it is eaſier to think then expreſſe: &amp; that he had beaten downe our maleuolent adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries with their own armor of Philoſophy and had ſhewed truth to be not only eaſie but favourable. Whileſt I did in ſilence runne over theſe things with my ſelfe, <hi>Cecilius</hi> broke forth and ſpake after this manner. I thanke <hi>octauius</hi> for the tranquility in which we are now like to liue, and I repute my ſelfe happy not expecting the deliuery of your ſentence. We haue all over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and I am forward to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpe the victory. For as he hath overcome me, ſo haue I made a triumhpe of errour,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:13003:87"/>
Therefore to the maine part of the queſtion I come in and ſay. That I acknowledge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, belieue in God, and conſent to the ſincerity of our ſect. Something yet remaines, not quarrelſome againſt truth but neceſſary for a perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; of which (becauſe the ſunne is now neare his declination) I ſhall to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row more conveniently and readily bee informed by you. Then ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, tis to me great ioy in all reſpects; <hi>Octavius</hi> hath done me a pleaſure in his victory, when hee hath ſo taken from me, the envy of being a judge, neither can I recompenſe his deſert with a verball praiſe. The acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one man is but a weake
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:13003:87"/>
teſtimony. God reward his owne gift; by him he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to ſpeake, and with his helpe he hath obtained this happy victory. After this we joyfully and merrily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. <hi>Cecilius</hi> becauſe hee now belieued, <hi>Octavius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had overcome, and I becauſe they both were ſo well pleaſd in their beliefe and victory.</p>
            <closer>Deo ſoli gracia.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:88"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:88"/>
            <head>A good Friday thought.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>I</hi> Thinke how Chriſt in his great pleaſure tooke</l>
            <l>A humane likeneſſe often in the booke</l>
            <l>Of mans creation, learning as it were,</l>
            <l>How in times fullneſſe Deity could beare</l>
            <l>The earneſt of our fleſh, in it be borne,</l>
            <l>Grow vp to three and thirty, then be torne</l>
            <l>With ſcourges and the croſſe, be crownd with thornes,</l>
            <l>Surprizd by treaſon and revild with ſcorns,</l>
            <l>Bee buffetted, bee ſpit on to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore</l>
            <l>Thoſe cruell actors to his loue and lore,</l>
            <l>From which both they and wee by ſerpents wile</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13003:89"/>In our firſt parents fall vntill this while</l>
            <l>For eating ſome forbidden fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall fruit,</l>
            <l>Figge, Peare, or Apple, which, I not dispute,</l>
            <l>Aſtoniſht with the wonder of Gods playe,</l>
            <l>Amongſt the ſonns of men, from whence well may</l>
            <l>We name our Gospell. He who framed all</l>
            <l>With one word, might without a funerall</l>
            <l>And paſſion of himſelfe ſo all repaire</l>
            <l>With one new pleaſing breath and gratefull aire.</l>
            <l>But ſince for humane ranſome he would die,</l>
            <l>I thus thinke on the ſacred hiſtory,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13003:89"/>As from the holy Moore I learne. Behold</l>
            <l>the price of mans redemption, and be bold,</l>
            <l>To bleſſe all nations, Chriſt his bloud pourd forth,</l>
            <l>What ranſome may be equall to ſuch worth?</l>
            <l>What but all tribes of men? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull they</l>
            <l>Or very proud, who dare or thinke, or ſay,</l>
            <l>Themſelues ſo great, or this ſo ſmall, that none,</l>
            <l>Should be by ſuch price ſavd but they alone.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="carol">
            <pb facs="tcp:13003:90"/>
            <head>A Chriſtmaſſe Caroll.</head>
            <l>Since now the jolly ſeaſon's by</l>
            <l>That giues and takes in curt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,</l>
            <l>I than haue nought to giue will ſing</l>
            <l>A caroll to our infant king,</l>
            <l>The Prince of peace, the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Lord,</l>
            <l>who all created with a word.</l>
            <l>And might ſo haue mankind redeemd,</l>
            <l>Had not another way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeemd,</l>
            <l>Which I adore not daring prie</l>
            <l>Jn ſecrets of Divinity.</l>
            <l>Haile bleſſed Virgin, mother milde,</l>
            <l>Which at this time didſt beare a childe,</l>
            <l>Who in the booke of Geneſis</l>
            <l>Doth bruiſe the head of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents hiſſe,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13003:90"/>And ſo as in allegorie</l>
            <l>Would their embleme Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire worie.</l>
            <l>His cradle was a manger, fed</l>
            <l>Where be the ſerpents, and doe bed</l>
            <l>In lothſome ordure neare, elſe place</l>
            <l>Should by <hi>Mariamnes</hi> grace</l>
            <l>In <hi>Herods</hi> ſofteſt downe haue beene</l>
            <l>For a fairer <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin Queene.</l>
            <l>Whoſe burden puzling natures eye.</l>
            <l>Made a new brightneſſe ſhine in skye,</l>
            <l>To guide three wiſe men rap't in ſenſe,</l>
            <l>With gold, with mirrhe, with frankomſenſe,</l>
            <l>From their Starre-gazing Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne ſtage</l>
            <l>To Bethlem in holy pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13003:91"/>When round about poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſwaynes</l>
            <l>Grazing their ſheepe on neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour plaines,</l>
            <l>Gods glory firſt by night did ſhow,</l>
            <l>And from an Angell let them know</l>
            <l>Tidings of ioy to all mankind,</l>
            <l>Which they in Davids towne ſhould finde.</l>
            <l>A ſwadling childe amongſt beaſtes ſtor'd,</l>
            <l>A Saviour which is Chriſt the Lord,</l>
            <l>Borne King of Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles all,</l>
            <l>Who in full time vnited ſhall</l>
            <l>Humbly vnto him bend, and praiſe,</l>
            <l>His triumphe with eternall layes.</l>
            <l>Of many proofes which make beliefe</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13003:91"/>In Chriſt ſo borne, this one is chiefe.</l>
            <l>The Iewes who ſcornd his low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y birth,</l>
            <l>Are skattered over all the earth,</l>
            <l>In falſe Chriſts oft by thouſand loſt,</l>
            <l>From on land to another toſt.</l>
            <l>Their Prieſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Scribes, all Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</l>
            <l>Which troubled were at birth of him,</l>
            <l>Haue loſt their Tribes, their Temple, ſtate,</l>
            <l>A people, outcaſt, runnagate.</l>
            <l>Now for one thouſand thirtie one</l>
            <l>And full ſix hundred yeares vndone.</l>
            <l>Bleſt infant, ſacred Deitie</l>
            <l>So ſhrouded in humanitie,</l>
            <l>Preſerue this new yeare to my friends</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13003:92"/>From thoughts ill ravelld into ends.</l>
            <l>Vouchſafe mee and my ſlender rimes,</l>
            <l>Not fawning on theſe faining times.</l>
            <l>Then ſhall I on thine Altar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly</l>
            <l>In Antheme of Aſcending day,</l>
            <l>As erſt J haue at Eaſter done,</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Threnothriambeuticon.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn">
            <head>A Hymne on Chriſts <hi>aſcenſion.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>TO thy paſſion and thy birth</l>
               <l>Bleſt Lord I haue two anthemes ſung,</l>
               <l>Once more to ſing in holy mirth</l>
               <l>Thy aſcending glory looſe my tongue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13003:92"/>That I with wonder and with praiſe,</l>
               <l>May ſett forth all thy holy daies</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Borne lowly, then on ſhamefull Croſſe</l>
               <l>By Iewes and Romans iudgd to dye,</l>
               <l>Jn birth or death not any loſſe,</l>
               <l>Empeacht thy immortalitye.</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Phebus</hi> after cloudes of raine,</l>
               <l>Thy God-head luſtred forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Aſcending thou to men didſt giue,</l>
               <l>To meaneſt men ſuch guifts of grace,</l>
               <l>As whether they did dye or liue,</l>
               <l>They forct all hearts in higheſt place,</l>
               <l>To proſtrate ſcepter, ſword and crowne</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13003:93"/>With worſhip to thy chiefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Poore fiſhermen of lakes that were</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>napt to ſway with eloquence,</l>
               <l>That knew not how to menace ſpeare,</l>
               <l>Or blandiſh words that raviſh ſenſe,</l>
               <l>Even theſe poore Heralds voyce did tame</l>
               <l>And winne all nations to thy name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I am lifted vp ſaith he</l>
               <l>In holy Goſpell of ſaint John,</l>
               <l>Then all men will J draw to me</l>
               <l>That is to his confeſſion.</l>
               <l>To heauen from cratch and croſſe he went,</l>
               <l>With men and Angells merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13003:93"/>
               <l>Triumphant lord no tongue, no thought,</l>
               <l>Can reach the wonder of thy wayes,</l>
               <l>But we muſt ſay as Paul hath taught,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thy euerlaſting praiſe,</l>
               <l>The myſterie of godlineſſe</l>
               <l>Is ſuch as no tongue can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God in the fleſh made manifeſt</l>
               <l>Jn the ſpirit iuſtified.</l>
               <l>Seene of the angells euer bleſt,</l>
               <l>To the Gentles verified.</l>
               <l>Believd on in the world his ſtory,</l>
               <l>Was vp receiued into glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
